<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The widow's mite, humbly offer'd, not impos'd; shewing by Scripture, why the seventh day of the Lord's rest is to be kept in Christ, under the Name Christian and Gospel Dispensation, and that Christ, which is Spirit, was one with the Father in creating ...</title>
            <author>Redford, Elizabeth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28831</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99882355</idno>
  <idno type="VID">189133</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264203374</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide T.1689[8]</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99882355</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99882355e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28831)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 189133)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C15:1[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The widow's mite, humbly offer'd, not impos'd; shewing by Scripture, why the seventh day of the Lord's rest is to be kept in Christ, under the Name Christian and Gospel Dispensation, and that Christ, which is Spirit, was one with the Father in creating ...</title>
                  <author>Redford, Elizabeth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690 or 1728]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Drop-head title.</note>
                  <note>Author's name taken from p. [36].</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing; item dated 1728 by ESTC.</note>
                  <note>P. 36 of item duplicated on film.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sabbath --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:189133:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:189133:1"/>
            <head>The <hi>WIDOW's MITE, Humbly osser'd, not impos'd;</hi> shewing by Scripture, why the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Day of the Lord's Rest is to be kept in Christ, under the Name <hi>Christian and Gospel Dispensation,</hi> and that Christ, which is Spirit, was one with the Father in creating, when God said, <hi>Come let us make Man,</hi> Gen. <hi>1.26. and their Sabbath of Rest, after six Days of their creating,</hi> ch. <hi>2.2, 3.</hi> and <hi>Exodus 16.23.</hi> and <hi>ch. 20.10.</hi> and many more Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; the seventh Day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God, not <hi>Jewish</hi> seventh Day, and was before <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile</hi> by Name was upon the Earth, or Sin entered the World; and the Day of their Rest hath never been abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, and the Commandments stand good, and are teached to this Day, as <hi>Exodus 20.</hi> sheweth.</head>
            <p>MANY hath been the Disputes, and still is, concerning the Lord's holy Rest, which Holy Rest is written with the Finger of God, and is a Weekly Sabbath, the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Day in the Commandments; and no Sabbath written with the Finger of God but the Lord's holy Rest in the Commandments, and is a Christian Sabbath under the Gospel, as under the Law, as joyning to the Lord in Worship, according to the Lord's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.2. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. <hi>and</hi> 20. the Commandments delivered to <hi>Moses,</hi> and the Lord hath sent his Son to bless his People, with the Incomes of his Spiritual Presence, but not to disannul the Ten Commandments and the Sound of the Angels; with the Angel of the Lord <hi>is Peace on Earth, Good-will towards Men,</hi> Luke 2.14.</p>
            <p>The other Sabbaths given the <hi>Jews</hi> under the Law, were given for several Services, to be kept in Holiness, and <hi>Moses</hi> delivered the Appointment of them Sabbaths, as he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Words from God, to deliver to the People, and to be observed in their several Months, and Weeks, and Monthly Sabbaths, of the New Moon and Yearly Feasts, but not Weekly any Sabbath to be kept in the Name of the Lord's holy Rest and Sabbath; but the Lord's holy Rest, which is every seventh Day, and the Lord hath commanded it to be kept holy, and calls for a remembrance upon it, not a seventh Day, but the seventh Day after six of Labour; and under the Gospel, the Resurrection of Jesus, which the Power of God did so gloriously appear, and maintained the Word of the Kingdom, in raising the Body the third Day, is worthy of remembrance; and to keep two Days in seven in Holiness, (each particular may hope to prosper the better in the other five Days) and to wait for the Resurrection of that Seed which gives Life and Resurrection to the waiting Soul, and so to receive the Word of the Kingdom in Spirit, and the baptizing Power of the Holy Ghost, which is the remembrancer, and gives fore-sight of every good Work; and so to wait, that that Power which raised <hi>Jesus</hi> from the Dead, may arise in each particular, and that all may so wait to know a Resurrection from the Death of Sin, and live to God in the Spirit which gives Life, and a glorious Resurrection when the Body dies; for it is the Body of Flesh which is prepared to die, the Spirit never dies, but goes to God which gave it Man to live by, of his own Substance Spiritual, and the Spirit descending in a universal man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at the Birth of Jesus, to visit them that <hi>waited for the Consolation of Israel,</hi> Luke 2.25. and is worthy of remembrance; and to bow before the Power of God, which sent the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to bless and inspire the People with the Word of God, which he received from God the anointing Power in him; and in that Word and Spirit he baptized the People with the Holy Ghost when he came in to his Ministry; and the Father and Son, which is the Holy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:189133:2"/> Ghost, spake in him and baptized the People, to follow the holy Example of Jesus, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Resurrection, that power in Jesus breathed on the Disciples, and said, <hi>receive ye the Holy Ghost;</hi> but did not call the first Day the seventh Day, nor a Sabbath Day, nor the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath Day, for the Sabbath is the Day before the Resurrection on the first Day of the Week, as the Body was crucified <hi>the Day before the Sabbath,</hi> Mark 15.42. and the holy Women returned, and prepared Spices and Ointments, and rested the Sabbath Day, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Commandment; and <hi>Matthew</hi> gives the Account, <hi>from the sixth Hour there was Darkness until the ninth Hour,</hi> ch. 27. v. 45. and 57. <hi>when the Even was come, Joseph of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathea, he went to Pilate and begged the Body of Jesus, and Pilate commanded the Body to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered;</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> gives the account, <hi>it was the third Hour, and they crucified him,</hi> ch. 15. v. 25. and 33. <hi>when the sixth Hour was come, there was a Darkness over the whole Land until the ninth Hour;</hi> so the third Hour and sixth Hour till the ninth Hour must be in the Morning, because they wondered at the Darkness, which if it had been Night, the Darkness was in its place. And <hi>when Even was come, because it was the Preparation, that is the Day before the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, Joseph of Arimathea, an honourable Councellor, which also waited for the Kingdom of God, craved the Body of Jesus,</hi> Mark 15.42. and <hi>Luke</hi> gives the account, <hi>it was about the sixth Hour, and there was a Darkness over all the Earth, and the Sun</hi> (ch. 23. v. 44.) <hi>was darkned:</hi> So this Darkness over all the Earth and Sun must be in the Morning, at the sixth and ninth Hour: and <hi>John</hi> gives the account, <hi>it was the Preparation, that the Bodies should not remain on the Cross on the Sabbath Day,</hi> ch. 19. v. 31. and all agree it was the ninth Hour that Jesus gave up the Ghost, and at the sixth Hour that Darkness was till the ninth Hour; and they all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that Jesus was crucified the Day before the Sabbath, and they all call the Day of the Resurrection of the Body the first Day of the Week, the Day after the Sabbath, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Crucifixion of the Bodily Presence. On the Sabbath Day the Chief Priests and Pharisees came together to <hi>Pilate,</hi> that he might command the Sepulchre to be made sure until the third Day, and their coming together was on the Sabbath, which they did not hold lawful to do any outward Business, according to the Commandments, but this being an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Thing, and the Judgment upon them great for what they had blindfoldly done, not discerning the Power which work'd within the Veil, but could not rest from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, discoursing the Matter, and seeking to secure the Sepulchre, and all Things was so suffered, that the Power of God might be made manifest in raising the Dead; but when the Angel descended, and roul'd away the Stone, the Power of God brought their Works to nothing. Men in every Generation have been disobedient, and made Trespasses in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they ought not, to their own Condemnation; but this does not make it lawful to break the Sabbath, the seventh Day of the Lord's rest; and as the Lord hath called the Days, I think it my Duty to call the Day, and I can't have a better Guide than to begin and end the Day as the Lord hath created it, and it appears to us in this lower Region, and as it stands recorded, and the Record hath been kept to by the Churches when they read the Law every Sabbath Day, and the Commandments written with the Finger of God, and his Power hath preserved a Record to his People to this Day, according to the Scripture Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and Signs of Heaven; and what one Word in the Ten Commandments is contrary to the Gospel, or the Spiritual Worship? And Men have seen the Work of God through his Angels and ministring Spirits, sent forth to them which shall be Heirs of Salvation, and he hath sent his Servants the Prophets to declare his Word, and to shew his Mind and Will, calling to Holiness, and Men have seen the Evening of the Law, and the Morning of the Gospel, which will both spring into a glorious Day, when the Love, Peace and Charity which is fixed in the Commandments takes place; which Peace points to the Gospel, which is for love to Neighbours, Unity and Peace, and to pray for Enemies; and the Lord's Words and Commands carry a Power with them, and hath ever made the Earth to tremble, and bow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and <hi>David</hi> and the Prophets were Witnesses of this great Word sent to both Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:189133:2"/> and People; and it is the Spirit and Word from God, from his Mouth immediately gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which will unite both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> to be one in the Work and Worship of God, and to see his Power over all his Works, and him to be the Creator, Redeemer and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier and Saviour of his People, through every Ministring Angel and Seer, through both the Law and Gospel to this Day; it is the Spirit of the Father which is in Christ his Son, which is all-saving, the Spirit of Grace, the Spirit of Truth, the Angel of his Presence, the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of an endless Life, King of Righteousness, King of Peace, the Spirit sent of the Father through the Son in Spirit, to work the Work of Reconciliation between God and Man, that Man might be redeemed from the Fall, to serve God in Spirit out of Sin, and follow the holy Pattern sent in the Flesh to be an Example, who delivered the Words of God, and spake as the Spirit gave him utterance, as the Disciples after did, as the Holy Ghost filled them with the Spirit and Words of Wisdom, to minister to the People; and they which are most in earnest with their own Soul please God best, and it is most for their peace, notwithstanding a Scholar may out-talk by Art an innocent Man, but the Secrets of God are with them that fear him, and he may out-word him one Time, yet keeping to the Grace, the Lord by his Word will help him to conquer another time, in the Faith and Patience, keeping to Truth the Spiritual Rock, and them which are teached in Christ's School, will prove the best Learning in the end, and he is the best Teacher which knows the Heart and the Infirmities of the Mind, and is a present help in the needful Time of Trouble, and when the Enemy comes in as a Flood, the Spirit of God will lift up a Standard against him, and cast him out with his rebellious Works; and as all joyn with the Spirit of the Lord, he will give them a Mind both to will and to do, and teach Man by his Spirit in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man, which is Christ's School, which Power will finish the Work as Man obeys the Power; and God is the same for ever, and the Day of his Rest the same, and never chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and the Commandments bear their Authority, being written with the Finger of God, and that part of the Law which consists in Ordinances, and of Sacrifices and Offerings is one thing, and the Ten Commandments is ever distinguished to be another; as the Law gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Moses</hi> very often does distinguish from Sacrifices which are Carnal, <hi>which were a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure for the time present, in which were offered both Gifts and Sacrifices, which could not make him that did the Service perfect, as pertaining to the Conscience, which stood only in Meats and Drinks, and divers Washings, and Carnal Ordinances, till the time of Reformation,</hi> Hebrews 9.9, 10. and if the Priest that did the Service was not perfected thereby, which was a Covenant-Offering to be accepted as Sin is forsaken, no more could the People without a perfect Heart be joyn'd to the Lord in Holiness and good Works, and as Light and Perfection was written upon <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Breast-plate, the <hi>Ʋrim</hi> and the <hi>Thummim,</hi> which <hi>Ʋrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> signifie Light and Perfection, pointing to the Kingdom of Christ, the Spirit of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, uniting in Spirit, through the Son, and shewing what it is makes perfect, and that it is Light and Perfection written in the Heart, and Christ one in Spirit with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is come the Spirit of Truth, and Light and Perfection is in him, which speaks to the Heart, he is the everlasting High-Priest, after the Order of <hi>Melchisedeck,</hi> and is in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of an endless Life, and not after the Order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> but is the faithful and true Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, giving account of Man's Deeds, and is a Witness in Man's Conscience on Earth, and he is a second Witness, the Book of Life, either to justifie the Good, or condemn the Evil, the Spirit of Truth is the Judge of both quick and dead, and the Holy One hath set an Example in Worship, speaking in Spirit, through the Veil, Man's Flesh out of Carnal Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, as the other Covenants was; and Christ in the Father, being Spirit as the Father is Spirit, they kept the Day of their Rest in Spirit, before Sin entered the World, as far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is mentioned; and after the Offerings of the Law, the Gospel is preached, and Christ the everlasting High-Priest is come, and the Works of the Spirit is preach'd, and the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship is still in the Spirit, and the same God that is the <hi>Alpha</hi> will be the <hi>Omega,</hi> and Christ
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:189133:3"/> is a Spirit and not Carnal, as the Offerings for Sin then were; and in its time the Lord did accept as Atonements for Carnal Sins, but under the Gospel, the Ministration in Spirit is sent in a universal manner to them that wait for that holy Power, the pure anointing Grace, and that which finds acceptance with the Father and Son, is a broken Heart and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite Spirit, and to tremble at his Word; and in the room of such Offerings for Peace and Sacrifices for Sin, the Light of Christ is a Lamp in his People, and the Fiery Baptism of the Holy Ghost, purges out Sin in all that wait for it, that they may appear before the Throne of Grace in Peace, in the one Offering and Mediator. And when the Lord rested the seventh Day, the World was but seven Days old, and as afore-written Sin had not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the World, and therefore no need of a Carnal Offering, as was after given the <hi>Jews,</hi> Sheep, and Oxen, and Kids of the Goats, Lambs and Rams, and Doves and Pidgeons, Offerings for Sin, and be Holy, for without Holiness no Man can see the Lord, and Christ the Holy One is come, the better Offering, and above all Carnal Offerings; and as God is not changed, so the Day of his Rest is not changed; and Christ the Spirit of Truth is High-Priest for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver after the Order of <hi>Melchisedeck, without Father, without Mother, without Descent, having neither beginning of Days nor end of Life, a High-Priest continually,</hi> Hebrews 7.2, 3. but the Veil to the Power and Spirit, had an espoused Father <hi>Joseph,</hi> and a fleshly Mother <hi>Mary,</hi> and had a Descent from the Loyns of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and down to <hi>Adam,</hi> and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded the Son of <hi>Adam</hi> as having a Body of Flesh, <hi>Matthew</hi> 1.19, 20. and after the Son of God, as he did the Works of God, and tasted Death upon the Cross, and to give place to the great Creator, the Power that worketh all things both in Heaven and Earth, is to keep the seventh Day of his Rest holy, and he put the Day of his Rest into a Command, and it was the first Day instituted for Divine Worship; and if it were but to remember the great Works of Creation, the seventh Day ought to be kept, and to remember the Sign given, that it is the same God which sanctifies the People, both Saints and Prophets, and by his Light preserves his Angels from Darkness, and hath given every Scripture from <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesis</hi> to the <hi>Revelations,</hi> the Author of every Mercy, through every Instrument sent, all is received from his Almighty Power, which sends both Men and Angels to bless the People, the Work of his Creation, and to give Glory to the Power, may be a means to bring the whole Vineyard of the Earth to grow, and to be of one Mind, in him that is true, and hath set an Example of keeping their Rest, and to see God in all his Attributes, as Almighty Lord God, and Creator, Redeemer and Saviour, <hi>Israel</hi>'s King; and to see the Power of God, in the Angel of his Presence, and the Word of God in every ministring Angel and ministring Spirit, Seer, or Man of God, or Prophet, sent, not to be another God, but to do the Will of God; and when the Lord, Creator, Redeemer and Saviour, his Mercy is seen in every Messenger sent, it will be a great means to set a stop to so many Divisions and Forms of Worship, and to see the end and sign of every Covenant, and to see what Covenants stand, and what Covenants appertaining to the Law is taken away; before there was any Law, the first Covenant is with Day and Night, and after the Bow in the Clouds, which remains a Sign that God will never totally drown the World, a wonderful Sign of his Power, and is ministred to the World as he pleaseth, and God renewed his Covenant to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and said, <hi>I am Almighty God, walk before me and be thou perfect,</hi> Gen. 17.1. <hi>as for me, my Covenant is with thee, and thou shalt be a Father of many Nations; I will make thee exeeeding fruitful; I will make Nations of thee, and Kings shall come out of thee,</hi> v. 7. <hi>I will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablish my Covenant between me and thee, and thy Seed after thee in their Generation, for an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Covenant, to be a God to thee and thy Seed after thee;</hi> and this Covenant stands, for Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus was of the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> according to the Flesh, and the Increase will be great, and God is now the sanctifier of his People which are faithful to him, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was; but Circumcision in the Gospel of Peace is taken off in the Flesh, <hi>Romans</hi> 4.11. notwithstanding, Jesus being of the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> received the Token of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:189133:3"/> that God would be a God to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed; and Jesus was circumcised the eighth Day, and when grown up to be a Man, received <hi>John</hi>'s Baptism of Water also, <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.14. and after he received the Water-Baptism, which he bid <hi>John suffer it to be so now,</hi> and after the Holy Ghost descended upon him, the Power in him baptized with the Holy Ghost and as <hi>John</hi>'s Baptism was in the room of Circumcision, so the Baptism of the Holy Ghost is prefer'd before <hi>John</hi>'s Water Baptism; and the Lord's Covenant to be a God to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed stands fast in <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.2, 3. <hi>thou shalt have no other Gods before me,</hi> and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Sign stands good, that it is God which sanctifieth his People, <hi>ch.</hi> 31.16, 17, 18. and <hi>ch.</hi> 34.28. <hi>and Moses was with the Lord forty Days and forty Nights, he neither eat Bread, nor drank Water, and he wrote upon the Tables the Words of the Covenant the Ten Commandments,</hi> Deut. 9.9. and the Lord renewed his Covenant made to <hi>Abraham, Isaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> to give them the Land, and the Lord appeared unto <hi>Moses</hi> by his Name <hi>Jehovah, Exod.</hi> 6.2, 3. <hi>and God spake to Moses, and said, I am the Lord, and I appeared to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, by the Name of God Almighty, but by my Name Jehovah was I not known to them:</hi> And God was pleased to make another Covenant with the House of <hi>Israel,</hi> which the Christians under the Gospel have a promise to share in, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. the <hi>Spirit to be poured forth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all Flesh;</hi> and the Lord hath made many Covenants with his People under several At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, his powerful Names, and as the Blood of Bulls, and Goats, and the Ashes of an Heifer is rejected, so the one Offering in Spirit is established, and the Spirit descends and ascends, and the Lord accepts of what he gives, and this is the new Covenant, the Law written in the Heart and put in the Mind, and the obedient ones they do the Will of God; but the Lord God and Creator, and the Day of his Rest, and the Ten Commandments are the same, notwithstanding the Day of their Rest are not kept by Nations, only a few bear Witness in keeping the seventh Day of his Rest after his great and mighty Works in creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and instituted a Day of Worship for Man to obey, before the Man of the Dust of the Ground was formed; and as to Offerings, the Apostle giving an Account of the Work wrought by the power of God in Jesus, or the Office of Christ, the ministration of the Spirit in him, <hi>wherefore when he cometh into the World, he saith, Sacrifice and Offerings thou wouldst not, but a Body hast thou prepared me; in Burnt-Offerings and Sacrifices for Sin thou hast had no pleasure: then said I, Lo I come, in the volume of the Book it is written of me, to do thy Will, O God; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, when he said, Sacrifice and Offerings, and Burnt-Offerings for Sin thou wouldst not, neither had pleasure therein; then said he, Lo I come to do thy Will, O God, he taketh away the first that he may establish the second,</hi> (and by doing the Will of God is the sanctification) <hi>by which Will we are sanctified</hi> (as saith the Apostle) they which are Spiritual are sanctified, <hi>through the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of the Body</hi> (Christ in Jesus) <hi>once for all,</hi> Hebrews 10.5. <hi>to</hi> 15. <hi>for by one Offering he hath perfected for ever them that are sanctified,</hi> (that is, as each particular that does the Will of God as he did, they are perfected by that Example, and sanctified in doing the Will of God according to that Example) <hi>whereof,</hi> saith the Apostle, <hi>the Holy Ghost is Witness;</hi> and saith the Apostle, <hi>ye have need of Patience, that after ye have done the Will of God ye might receive the Promise,</hi> ver. 36. so the offering the Body once for all is, that Man should be sanctified in Body, Soul and Spirit, to follow the holy Obedience of Jesus, or they have no part in his Sufferings; and the Offering in Spirit is established by the Office of Christ, the Power of God, the power of an endless Life, a spiritual Ministration in his waiting ones, the Law written in the Heart, and put in the Mind, and this Covenant and Offering salted with the seasoning Grace, the Fiery Baptism of the Holy Ghost, which cannot lose its savour; <hi>for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one shall be salted with Fire, and every Sacrifice shall be salted with Salt; Salt is good▪ but if the Salt have lost its saltness, wherewith will you season it, have Salt in your selves, and have Peace one with another,</hi> Mark 9.49, 50. Matt. 5.13. Levit. 2.13. neither shalt thou suffer the Salt of the Covenant of thy God to be lacking, with all thy Meat Offerings thou shalt offer Salt, and without the Covenant of Salt to every Meat Offering, it was not to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:189133:4"/> and when the Offerings were accepted of the Lord, there came Fire from before the Lord as a sign of Acceptance, and it humbled the People, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.38. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Levit.</hi> 9.24. and gave them Faith to believe, as Faith is the Gift of God, and they saw the Works of the true God, and <hi>by Faith Abel offered unto God a more excellent Sacrifice than</hi> Cain, <hi>by which he obtained Witness that he is righteous, God testifying of his Gifts, and by it he being dead, yet speaketh,</hi> Heb 11.4. Gen. 4.4. and under the Gospel Law, the seasoning Grace of Faith is both Salt and Fire, purifying both Heart and Mind to see that Life and Light which is everlasting; for in the Holy One's Seed there is no Corruption; and the Apostle speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Offering the Body prepared to do the Will of God, (in the Works of the Spirit which works and purges out Sin, as all are obedient to the Works of the Spirit) he makes the first Offering for Sin, the old Covenant, such as Blood of Bulls, Lambs, Sheep and Goats, and Rams, and Pidgeons, and the Ashes of an Heifer; <hi>for the Law having a Shadow of the good Things to come, and not the very Image of the things, can never with these Sacrifices which they offer Year by Year continually, make the comers thereunto perfect, for then would they not have ceased,</hi> Heb. 10.1, 4. so that the Apostle treating of the first Covenant of Sacrifices and Offerings, (which if the Heart and Ear were circumcised) such found Acceptance in their Obedience, and then Offerings ceased. The Apostle did not here treat upon the Ten Commandments, which remains, and the Sabbath a Sign, that God is the God which doth sanctifie his People, as afore-written; and the Day of his Rest a Sabbath, in remembrance of the six Days of his Creation, in honour due to his great creating Name; as the great Creator of Heaven and Earth, the Seas and the Fountains of Water, the Almighty God, the Lord of Heaven and Earth, the <hi>I am,</hi> and the <hi>Jehovah,</hi> he hath commanded the Day of his glorious Rest to be kept; look into it, see the Disobedience the World lieth in, and till Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are seen in the universal Love and come to keep the Commandments, the Holy Rest in Holiness, Wars will never cease; and saith the Apostle, as speaking of the Power descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding when he cometh into the World, he saith, <hi>A Body hast thou prepared me to do thy Will, O God;</hi> and Jesus was that Body prepared for the Spirit to work in; and in this Body prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Word of God appeared, to inspire them which received it, and they became Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses in the Spirit, of the Works of the Spirit and Power of God, the new Covenant wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in Man, in the universal Love and Light, not only to Witnesses and Prophets, which were Witnesses of the Power of God, and so Christ's Day; but to all which receive the Word, and wait for it, they are inspired by it; Christ is the Spirit of God in Man, the <hi>Immanuel</hi> God with us, and God with us is the Spirit of Truth; and Jesus foretold his Disciples, <hi>he that dwelleth with you shall be in you,</hi> John 14.16, 17. and they were after filled with the Holy Ghost, and spake as the Spirit gave them utterance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as Christ was in Jesus, the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, the Spirit of Truth, so Christ the Lord was in all the Prophets, and the People were to be begotten into the Word and universal Spirit in the inward Man, the Dispensation of the Father through the Son, which Son is Spirit and not Flesh, but is the Spirit which quickens and speaks now in Man, the Words of Spirit and Life, and this Word is Spirit and Life in every Work of God; and notwithstanding the Church under the Gospel, as Saints and Prophets is come, and many coming to Mount <hi>Zion</hi> to which the Apostle gives witness of, yet they went through many Steps in Grace before they knew a coming <hi>to the general Assembly and Church of the First-born, which are written in Heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the Spirits of just Men made perfect; and to Jesus Christ the Mediator of the new Covenant, and to the Blood of Sprinkling, that speaketh better things than that of Abel,</hi> Heb. 12.22, 23, 24. and saith the Apostle, <hi>ye are come unto Mount Zion, and to the City of the living God, the heavenly Jerusalem, and to an innumerable Company of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, to the general Assembly and Church of the First-born, which are written in Heaven;</hi> and the City belonging to this Church is the heavenly <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and the Assembly before the Judge of all, is an innumerable Company of Angels, which is the Spirits of just Men made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:189133:4"/> which is a gradual Work; but to miss the First Day, instituted for divine and spiritual Worship, when God rested in himself and all his Works which he had made, and behold they were very good, and to miss the first Step, as afore-written, is not to get the higher degree of Grace and Peace in the Holy Ghost, which gives Admittance through the Names of <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> into the Gospel; and them which were of the Twelve Tribes, a certain Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of every Tribe sealed the Father gave the Son; <hi>and John saw upon Mount Zion, the Lamb stood with them, which had his Father's Name written in their F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reheads,</hi> Rev. 14.1. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the Father is pleased to give them which were his, both the Tribes, and Saints, and Prophets under the Law, to the Son and Word, to unite in the spiritual Building, the heavenly <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and when the Sin is subdued, and all brought into the Spirit of the Son to obey the Words of God, the Son is then to deliver up the Kingdom to the Father, which gave him Power to gather into the Kingdom of God, to the Lord of Hosts, the God of both Angels and Men, the eternal and everlasting Being of Beings, the one God which is Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and the Day of his Rest to be held in everlasting Remembrance of his great Works of Creation, and he is also the Redeemer of his People from Generation to Generation, it is his Mercy through every Instrument sent in his Power to save the People in every Age.</p>
            <p>The Lord being pleased of his wonderful Goodness to call me to keep the Seventh Day of his Rest a Holy Sabbath to the Lord, out of Labour, according as the Commandment stands good; and I pondered the Weight of the Matter in my Mind, and could not go on in outward Business on that Day; and as I pondered the Weight of the Matter in my Mind, it opened more and more, and Scriptures were opened in my View, and I was more and more enlightened, in the Light which the Scriptures gives both in the Old Testament and the New; and it was given me to distinguish between the Lord's holy Rest and the <hi>Jews</hi> Sabbaths, given them to afflict for Sin, and them Sabbaths abolished in the one Offering to them which believe in the Gospel Dispensation, following the holy Example of Jesus, (and Sin is also to be abolished in the Mind); but the Lord's Sabbath of holy Rest before Sin was, is not abolished, for the holy Rest is in Christ the Spirit of Truth, which rested in the Father, the Seventh Day, after Six Days of their Creation; and the Lord was pleased to open my Understanding to see the true Record of the right Seventh Day were preserved, and the Account given by himself, and written with the Finger of God, and that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments are teached and preached and not kept; all which I laid up in my Heart, and kept the Seventh Day, and did not let any know for a considerable Time that I did keep it, and I thought to keep a Day to the Lord, according to the Commandments, was no hurt to any, but I found it did quiet my Mind to obey the Call; but when Work was to be done on that Day, I was then made to own the keeping the Seventh Day, by refusing to do any outward Business upon the Seventh and First Day of the Week; the First Day (known by the Name of <hi>Sunday</hi>) I had always observed, and grew strongly convinced in the keeping of both, and I obeyed the Voice and searched the Scriptures, and dare not hide the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of either; and when it was known, many argued with me against keeping the Seventh Day, calling it <hi>Jewish</hi> Seventh Day; but when I asked them if it was called the <hi>Jewish</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Day in the Ten Commandments? they answered No; then I had reason enough to ask them, Why they called the Lord's Rest <hi>Jewish?</hi> And some would ask if there were more Sabbaths? I then answered Yes, many Sabbaths given the <hi>Jews</hi> to afflict for Sin, and called their Sabbaths, and Sabbaths to rejoice in at the ingathering of the Corn and Fruits of the Earth; they held Sabbaths which were given them to rejoice in, at which they had set Feasts of Charitable Acts, and the Widow and Fatherless, and Stranger were to partake with them of the Blessings and the Increase, after the Priest had waved a Sheaf before the the Lord, on the Morrow after the Sabbath, which Morrow after the Sabbath was the First Day, and may tipify then another Sabbath for Acts of Charity and Mercy, to be heal'd
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:189133:5"/> in the Christian Faith, under the Gospel of Peace; and the Apostles appointed holy Men to take Care of the Widows, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.1, 2. And the Lord had a People in Christ under the Law, as also under the Gospel, if they are led and guided by the Spirit, as in Days of Old; the Record in Scripture is <hi>Isa.</hi> 60.11. and <hi>Isaiah</hi> see largely the further coming of Christ's Kingdom, and the powerful Effects of God's Majesty, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.19, 21. and the great Dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation of the Spirit of Christ <hi>Isaiah</hi> was a Witness of, <hi>Ch.</hi> 42.5. and <hi>Ch.</hi> 40.10, 11. and <hi>Ch.</hi> 61. and which Spirit should be universal, and to increase to them which are led and guided by the Spirit, the holy One in the Father, the Creator, Redeemer, and Saviour and King, <hi>Isa.</hi> 43.10. to the 16th <hi>Ver.</hi> God did not leave himself without a Witness, nor his People without a Christ to be a Guide to <hi>Israel</hi> under the Law, and the Lord's Sabbath of holy Rest is in Christ and Christ in the Father, before there was a visible Man upon the Earth; and as Christ was with the Father, a Spirit in the Beginning creating, he is in his People given him of the Father to this Day, leading up the Flock, as in Days of Old he put his holy Spirit within them, and led them by the right Hand of <hi>Moses</hi> with his glorious Army, dividing the Waters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, to get himself an everlasting Name, through the Power which God had given him, leading <hi>Israel</hi> through the Sea in a Pillar of Fire, but their holy Rest is not abolished that it should not be kept holy the Seventh Day, for Christ in Jesus did not appear in that prepared Body to lessen the Father's Honour with his own; as to the Day of his Rest com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be kept holy as the Lord's holy Rest after Six Days of their creating, in which he made Heaven and Earth, the Sea and the Fountains of Water, and all that in them is; but the Father giving the Son Power under the Gospel, sheweth the Works of the Power is to be observed, and hath added by the Resurrection of Jesus in the Power of God▪ an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Day for Worship, and the Resurrection of Jesus to be held in everlasting Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, in which the Works of the Power are seen, and Jesus is a holy Example, a Vail for the Word to pass through, a holy Prophet, and sent in a universal Spirit, the Morning Star in preaching and publishing the Gospel, but not to disanul the Father's Commandments. Thus to the Inquirer I declared my Satisfaction, and at length there was a Book brought to my Hand, called <hi>A Defence of the Christian Sabbath,</hi> and by this Book I understand the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion is, Whether it be the right Seventh Day in Course from the Creation? and that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords may be lost; and the Author of that Book is pleased to call it <hi>Jewish Sabbath,</hi> and <hi>Jewish Seventh Day;</hi> and upon reading the Book, the Weight of the Matter continued, and more Strength was given me to see the Sabbath is in Christ, which rested with the Father before the visible Man was formed, and there is no Sabbath out of Christ the holy Spirit, one with the Father in Spirit from the Creation, and that God which created the Day and rested in himself, gave the right Record of the Seventh Day, after the Destruction of the old World for Sin, both at the raining of <hi>Manna</hi> and the <hi>Commandments,</hi> written with the Finger of God, and given to <hi>Moses</hi> upon <hi>Mount Sinai.</hi> And upon reading the Books as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned, it pleased God to give me Weight to observe the Discourse, and the Sense which God was pleased to continue to me, I was made to write in the Confirmation of the Fourth Commandment, and that the Lord's holy Rest is not abolished, nor called <hi>Jewish Seventh Day</hi> in the Commandments, nor <hi>raining of Manna;</hi> and the Commandments written with the Finger of God is to continue under the Gospel, and whilst there is an <hi>Alpha</hi> and an <hi>Omega,</hi> and Man upon the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.13, 14. and the Lord of Hosts, the God both of Angels and Men, he will stand by them which keep their holy Rest holy; and the Lord's holy Rest is proved by Scripture to be the same from <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. to <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. and from the raining of Manna to the Commandments, because the Lord gave the Account himself by his Word to <hi>Moses</hi> to give to the People, and after the Lord had fixed the Commandments in the Peoples Hearts, and upon Tables of Stone, to be remembred, the Prophets all came in the Word of the Lord, and down to the Birth of Jesus, confirming the keeping the Lord's
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:189133:5"/> holy Rest, which is a Christian Sabbath in the Dispensation of the Father, his Spirit through the Son, and the Son in Spirit through the Son of Man, and the Father and Son in Spirit, one in the Creation of Mankind, and one in Redemption; and the Four Evangelists give an Account of the crucifying that prepared Body, and waiting for the Resurrection; they all give an Account of the Sabbath the Day before the Resurrection; and, as afore-writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the Seventh Day is a Christian Sabbath to them which keep it in Christ, and Christ is the Angel of Power, the spiritual Rock which was with <hi>Moses,</hi> and all them which live, and act, and obey the Voice of the inspeaking Spirit, with holy Minds, and pure Hearts, and clean Hands, such was ever in Christ, as Christ is ever with the Father, the Word of God, <hi>but without Holiness no Man can see the Lord,</hi> nor worship the Father with Acceptance out of the Spirit of Christ, and to keep the Commandments of God, the Lord's holy Rest, as he set an Example, when this lower World was but seven Days old; and Christ is given of the Father in this universal Day, the pouring forth the Spirit upon Sons and Daughters, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Hand-Maids, a Light in their People, and moves in the inward Man, which keeps their Obedience, and is leading up the Flock to the Father, as Man obeys the Voice; and the Lord's Sabbath of holy Rest was a Christian Sabbath under the Law, to them that kept it in Christ the Spirit of the holy One; that is, to worship the Father in the Spirit of the Son, the one Mediator which finds Acceptance with the Father; and the Lord's Command is to obey his Voice, or he will not pardon your Transgressions, <hi>for my Name is in him, saith the Lord,</hi> and the People was to do all that the Lord spake through him, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. and 21. and notwithstanding the Word of God, Christ the Lord, in Jesus speaking to the People of God, saying, <hi>Thine they were, and thou gavest them me, and they have kept thy Word; now they know that all Things whatsoever thou hast given me are of thee, for I have given unto them the Words which thou gavest me, and they have received them, and have known surely that I came out from thee, and they have believed that thou didest send me,</hi> John 17.6, 7, 8. And yet before they were so given of the Father in the Ministration of the Gospel, Christ was leading up the Flock in Days of old, <hi>Isa.</hi> 63.9. <hi>Israel</hi> did eat their spiritual Meat and drink their spiritual Drink through Leaders, which obeyed the Voice and see their Salvation by their Obedience to the Power, <hi>and they drank of the spiritual Rock that followed them, and that Rock was Christ,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.3, 4. the People were not without a Christ to lead and guide them, nor without spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Meat; for, as afore-written, the Gospel Record is, <hi>Israel did all eat the same spiritual Meat, and did all drink the same spiritual Drink,</hi> they then drank of the Rock of Ages in that ministration, as many now do drink deep Draughts of that Rock and Fountain in this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Gospel Day, the Dispensation of both Father and Son in the Gospel of Peace, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Example of Jesus in obedience to the Spirit, according to their Gift what is requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of them; God hath not left himself without a Seed, nor are his People saved but by his Power in every Dispensation of both Angels and Men: And Jesus in Prayer to the Father saith, <hi>Glorify thy Son, that thy Son also may glorify thee, and this is Life eternal,</hi> (saith Jesus) John 17.13. <hi>that they might know thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom thou hast sent;</hi> and this is the great Work to this Day, to distinguish the Spirit's working in Man, so to know thee the only true God and Jesus Christ whom thou hast sent, this is Life eternal; and when any comes to distinguish the spiritual Power, which is a Voice in Man, the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit to Salvation, such will the better see the Lord's Sabbath of holy Rest is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Sabbath, when Christ which ever was Spirit, rested in the Father, and the Father in him, one Spirit; and this Sabbath of their holy Rest before Sin entered the World, and to be kept in Remembrance of the sixth Day of their Creation and holy Rest, before Sin en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the World, and hath no relation to the <hi>Jews</hi> Sabbaths, given them to afflict for Sin, called their Sabbaths, nor any relation to their Carnal Ordinances and Sacrifices for Sin, these are Sabbaths given to that End, as aforementioned, and bear the Name of <hi>Jewish Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths;</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:189133:6"/> but <hi>the Sabbath of the Lord thy God, which thou art commanded to keep, is a holy Sabbath, and to be kept holy,</hi> as <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. sheweth; and that Chapter does not give any Authority to call the Lord's Sabbath a <hi>Jewish</hi> Sabbath, when the Lord hath called it <hi>the Sabbath of the Lord thy God,</hi> and the spiritual Male and Female, in their Likeness, and after their Image rested in Spirit with both Father and Son the seventh Day, before the visible Man of the Dust of the Ground was formed, or made Woman out of Man; their Image and Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness was in their Rest, and the Body of Dust goes to the Grave, the Spirit, which is Man's Light and Life, returns to God which gave it, to be a Light and a Guide to Man, to lead him into all Truth; and the Dispensation of the Father is in the Son, and the Son is in Presence, the Angel of God speaking the Words of God, and visits the Seed of God, teaching the Inward Man, and the visible Man is enlightened and saved in God's Power, as he keeps his Obedience in the Growth of the Spirit, and the Father draws into the Spirit of the Son in this Gospel Day, and the Father and Son, which is the Holy Ghost, speaks in each Particular, which wait to hear the Voice of their Word; but the seventh Day of their holy Rest is not abolished, as is further shewed after six Days of their creating of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in the room of the <hi>Jewish</hi> Sabbath, a Day to afflict their Souls for Sin, as under the Law, in the room of such Sabbaths, is the Fiery Baptism of the Holy Ghost, purging out Sin under the Gospel; and as the Fiery Baptism of the Holy Ghost purges out Sin (and gives in the Mind) Affliction for Sin, so it sanctifies the Soul into the true Rest, to keep the Lord's Sabbath of Rest holy, as owned and commanded, and this Baptism after received, is a continual Light to the Soul, and the Lord was the Sanctifier of his People under the Law, which obeyed his Voice through Leaders, (and afflicted their Souls for Sin), and the People heard the Voice of the Lord through the Fiery Pillar, that they might obey his Voice through <hi>Moses,</hi> and under the Gospel Ministration, the Spirit of Truth is heard in each Particular, convincing and shewing Men their Sin, and the Way out of Sin; and that which convinces and shews Men their Sin, is the Life and the Way to the Father, a Light shining in the Mind and Soul of Men, and the Fiery Baptism of the Holy Ghost does perform in Man the Office which them Days were appointed for to afflict the Soul for Sin, but the Lord's holy Rest, before Sin entered the World, is to be obeyed as commanded; and all Mankind are to labour to get out of Sin and to live to God in the Spirit of their Minds, and obey the Father through the Son, for the Father is the Creator, Redeemer and Saviour, which hath sent the Son to save, but never altered the Day of their holy Rest, from the seventh Day to the first Day of the Week; and no Day written by the same Finger of God, as the Commandments are, and commanded to be kept, and a Remembrance to keep the Day of his Rest holy; no Day appointed or written with the Finger of God, to be kept in the room of the seventh Day, or that the seventh Day should be abolished when the first is kept. But there are many Queries concerning the seventh Day, and that the right seventh Day is not known, because Records may be lost, and, as aforementioned, call it <hi>Jewish Seventh Day,</hi> and yet say they don't speak against the seventh Day in the Fourth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and by so saying, it may be reasonable to think such have not yet distinguished be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Lord's holy Rest and the <hi>Jews</hi> Sabbath, given them to afflict their Souls for Sin, which holy Rest was before Sin entered the World; and therefore all ought to be prepared in Holiness to keep the Lord's Rest holy, and in exercising a Day to afflict the Soul for Sin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, in the room of them Sabbaths, under the Gospel Ministration, as afore-written; the Spirit of Truth is sent down to convince the World of Sin, and to shew each Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar the Way out of Sin, and to baptize the Soul into its own Spirit, and is the Truth, the Life, and the Way to the Father; and what could the Lord do more for his Creation, than send his Son, the Spirit of Truth a Light to shine in their Hearts which obeys the Voice? it leads to the Father. And now the Lord is calling to the Preachers of all sorts, to see if they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:189133:6"/> have salt in themselves to savour the Earth; and he is looking down upon all the Honest-hearted, and to be Honest-hearted is more than Form; and Men may snatch away their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety one from another, but they can't snatch away the Kingdom of God from coming to them which wait for it; and the Words of God sent down are the Keys of the Kingdom, and opens the Mysteries of the Kingdom, and an Eye to see the Wisdom and Power of God through every Dispensation and Generation and Instrument sent in the Power of God; it is one God which is the Creator, Redeemer, and Sanctifier, and Saviour; for as it is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God which creates, so it is the Sanctifier, Redeemer and Saviour, and in Holiness there is Salvation, as the holy Example Christ in Jesus is lived to, that is, as the Spirit which acted in Jesus, and by which Spirit he spoke is lived to; and I have seen a Unity in Heaven to descend upon Men upon Earth, and Christ the Spirit of Truth will be the Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Star in this Unity; and among every People and Nation they that fear God, and obey the Spirit's Teachings, God will work a Work in them which some will not believe, altho it be told them, but the Work will go on to the Calling the <hi>Jews</hi> and convincing the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that all may come to see the one true God, and Christ from the Vail, and God from Man, and Flesh from Spirit, and the Messenger from the Maker, and the Land to enjoy her Sabbaths again, and Mercy is promised to Thousands, which love <hi>God and keep his Commandments,</hi> and are not found in their Father's Iniquities, and (the Commandment) in keeping their holy Rest, and to shew Love to Neighbours, and Charity to the Widows, and Fatherless, and the Stranger in the Gate; and Rest to both Son and Daughter, Servant and Cattel, was never disanul'd by neither Son nor Servant, sent in the Words of God; and it was the Will of the Holy Ghost, which sent the Prophet like unto <hi>Moses;</hi> and Jesus was anointed with the Holy Ghost, and in that Power went about doing Good, and the Holy Ghost sent forth under the Gospel universal Love, the Promise of the Father descended, which is the Holy Ghost, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.33. And the Body of Jesus being taken up, which was anointed and acted by the Holy Ghost; so the Son, one with the Father in Spirit, is seen with a spiritual Eye, leading to Holiness, by his Holy Spirit, and is calling to Men, working Peace and Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with the Father; and if Men will obey the Angelick Present, and Power given, it draws into Holiness, and Wisdom is justified of her Children, and the Work of Wisdom increase upon them, till they come to a State of a perfect Man in Christ, following Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; and as Christ is in God the Word of God so he visits Man in his season, and as Man grows in Grace and Truth, to see both the Father and Son, and growing in the Degrees of Grace, Life from God is given, and they are united into the Father's Love, and in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Christ are Witnesses of the Word, which quickens, and are Spirit and Life; and the Testimony of Jesus is the Spirit of Prophecy, and both Lord and Christ was in him, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing filled with the Holy Ghost, and he manifested both Lord and Christ in the Power of the Holy Ghost, the Promise of the Father, and the Promise of the Father descended upon him, and in him and through him, before he ascended, and the Disciples were baptized of the Holy Ghost, through the Words of God which was with him; and after Jesus ascend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Disciples were to wait for that Baptism; and the Father which sent the Son, is pleased the Son's Spirit and Word should be honoured, keeping a Day to do good Works, and to wait for the Resurrection of the Seed of Life, that they may be accepted in every good Work wrought through the Workings of the Holy Ghost, and according to the many Testimonies of Jesus; he spoke not of himself, and he proves the Prophet, which the Lord promised to send like unto <hi>Moses,</hi> speaking the Words <hi>the Lord had commanded him,</hi> Deut. 18.18. and it was the Power that spoke through the Vail, which said, <hi>I am the Resurrection and the Life,</hi> John 17.8. (it is the Spirit gives Life), and the same Power speaking through him, said, <hi>before A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham was I am;</hi> and the Power and Spirit said, <hi>I am the Way, the Truth and the Life,</hi> and the Vail to the Word being holy and obedient in Spirit, is a Light to the World, and speaks to this Day; and the Apostles and Saints after Jesus was taken up, were known to be san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:189133:7"/> Vessels, by the Works wrought through them; and the Generations keeps up Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks of the Saints works, and keeps Days in Honour and Remembrance of them, as is far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shewed; but the Lord Sanctifier and Creator, the Day of his Rest is not kept, nor his Command obeyed, in keeping the Seventh Day; when all the Apostles, their Fasts and Feasts, are observed to be kept in their Order: as <hi>Mark</hi> the Evangelist; <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>James</hi> the Apostles; the Ascension of our Lord Christ in Jesus; <hi>Barnabas;</hi> the Nativity of <hi>John Baptist; Peter</hi> the Apostle; <hi>James</hi> the Apostle; <hi>Bartholom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w</hi> the Apostle; <hi>Matthew</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle; <hi>Michael</hi> and all Angels; <hi>Luke</hi> the Evangelist; <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> the Apostle; All Saints; <hi>Andrew</hi> the Apostle; <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apostle; the Nativity of Jesus; <hi>Stephen</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr; <hi>John</hi> the Evangelist; Holy <hi>Innocents;</hi> The Purification of the Blessed Virgin: The Annunciation of the Virgin, after the Day of Pentecost. Now to shew that Jesus and his Disciples and the holy Women did observe to keep the Sabbath of holy Rest, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they did desire greatly to see the Resurrection of Jesus, yet they rested the Sabbath. And Jesus that great Prophet and Son, in his Ministry and Testimony, speaking the Words of God, owned the Sabbath of Rest for Man; he said, <hi>The Sabbath was made for Man, and not Man for the Sabbath. Therefore the Son of Man is Lord also of the Sabbath,</hi> Mark 2.27. And the four Evangelists gives an Account which is the Sabbath, and which is the First Day of the Week: <hi>In the end of the Sabbath, as it began to dawn towards the first Day of the Week, came Mary Magdalen, and the other Mary, to see the Sepulchre,</hi> Mat. 28.1. Mark 16.1. <hi>And when the Sabbath was past, Mary Magdalen, and Mary the Mother of James, and Salome, had brought sweet Spices, that they might come and anoint him.</hi> And ver. 9. <hi>When Jesus was risen early, the first Day of the Week, he appeared first to Mary Magdalen, out of whom he had cast se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Devils.</hi> And <hi>Luke</hi> 23.55, 56. <hi>The Woman also which came with him from Galilee, beheld the Sepulchre, and how his Body was laid, and they returned and prepared Spices, and Ointments, and rested the Sabbath Day, according to the Commandment.</hi> And Chapter 24.1. <hi>Ʋpon the first Day of the Week, very early in the Morning, they came to see the Sepulchre, bringing the Spices which they had prepared, and certain others with them.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> 19.31. <hi>The Jews because it was the Preparation, that the Bodies should not remain upon the Cross, besought Pilate they might be token away.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> 20.1. <hi>The first Day of the Week cometh Mary Magdalen early, when it was yet dark, unto the Sepulchre, and seeth the Stone taken away from the Sepulchre.</hi> So that which is the Seventh Day, and the first Day of the Week, the Scriptures of both Old and New Testament doth clearly show. And it is written in the Account of the Creation, the six Days Work and the Seventh Day's Rest; and on the sixth Day, the spiritual Male and Female, in their Image, and after their Likeness, rested in the Lord's Rest, and remaine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in his Rest, and in the good Spirit, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26, 31. But the visible Man <hi>Adam,</hi> from the Dusts of the Ground, was not yet made, till after the Seventh Day's Rest, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.1. which Dust of the Ground was another Region in the lower World; which their Image and Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness was not: for the Record is, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.6. <hi>There was not a Man to till the Ground; and there went up a Mist from the Earth, and watered the whole Face of the Ground.</hi> And when the visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Man <hi>Adam</hi> was made of the Dust of the Ground, the visible Woman <hi>Eve</hi> was not yet made: <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.18. <hi>The Lord God said, It is not good, that the Man should be alone, I will make him an Help-meet for him.</hi> So that the visible Male and Female was not formed, nor made till after the seven Day's Rest. And in the six Days Work, <hi>the Lord God saw every thing that he had made, and behold it was very good; and the Even and the Morning were the sixth Day, and all the Host of Heaven, and every thing upon Earth glorified God,</hi> in Purity; and on the Seventh Day God ended his Works which he had made; and God blessed the Seventh Day, and san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified it; because that in it he had rested from all his Works which God created and made. And Man had no hand in all this Work, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.4. sheweth; <hi>These are the Generations of the Heavens and of the Earth, when they were created: in the Day when the Lord God made the Earth and the Heavens, and every Plant of the Field, before it was in the Earth, and every Herb of the Field be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:189133:7"/> it grew: for the Lord God had not caused it to Rain upon the Earth, and there was not a Man to Till the Ground.</hi> Notwithstanding Male and Female, <hi>In their Image and Likeness was,</hi> Gen. 1.27. <hi>God created Man in his own Image; in the Image of God created he him, Male and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male created he them.</hi> For as God is a Spirit, so their Image is Spirit, and returns to him; which the Dust of the Ground does not, as is seen it remains in the Ground; but the spiritual Male and Female never dies, but keeps his Dominion in Light and Life: And when <hi>Adam</hi> the visible Man? was <hi>formed of the Dust of the Ground, the Lord God breathed into his Nostrils the Breath of Life; and Man</hi> (in that living Seed) <hi>became a living Soul:</hi> So that the Sabbath for Divine and Spiritual Worship, was before the formed Man of the Dust of the Ground was. And it is certain, the Sabbath was made for the visible Man, and not the visible Man before the Sabbath: the seventh Day of the Lord's holy Rest, and the Creation of Angels, the heavenly Host worshipped God in Spirit (as God is a Spirit); and the Angelical spiritual Male and Female in their Image, and after their Likeness, (Light and Life) was created be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord's Rest, and did rest when the Lord rested, which was before the visible Man was formed of the Dust of the Ground; and this Light and Life their Image gives Presence and Life, in the visible Male and Female, and is a Seed to inlighten both Male and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, a spiritual Seed in the Light of Christ; and this is the visible Man's Peace and Rest to this Day; as all are obedient to the Spirit, their Image and Likeness: and the Words of God is the Candle of the Lord to Man, a Lanthorn to his Feet and a Light to his Paths: And as the spiritual Worship is the first Worship, so it will be the last Worship, and he that is the <hi>Alpha</hi> he will be the <hi>Omega,</hi> the first and the last in Man's Earth: And Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man joining to the good Spirit in them, are preserved by the Words of God, through the Mouth of the Seed, and the Seed visiting Seed, this Word gives Life to the Soul; and the Seed of Life, which receives the Words of God, and gives forth the Words of God, is God's Image, and after their Likeness, and never consents to sin: Notwithstanding the visible Man <hi>Adam</hi> did fall, and after the Fall of the visible <hi>Adam,</hi> the Curse and Destruction for their sakes, came upon the Earth, the old World (and the World increased again, and a righteous Seed preserved) but as the Wickedness of Man was great in the Earth; <hi>And God saw that every Imagination of the Thoughts of Mans Heart was only evil continually: and it repented the Lord that he had made Man on the Earth; and it grieved him at his Heart,</hi> Gen. 6.5, 6, 7. And as the Lord destroyed the World for Man's Wickedness, yet <hi>Noah</hi> and his Sons obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Blessing through the righteous Seed, and to <hi>be fruitful and multiply; and replenish the Earth.</hi> Gen. 9.1. <hi>And the whole Earth was of one Language, and one Speech.</hi> Gen. 11.1. <hi>And they said one to another, Let us make Brick, and build us a City, and a Tower whose Top may reach unto Heaven; and let us make us a Name, lest we be scattered abroad upon the Face of the whole Earth.</hi> And this is Man's Misery, the way which he proposes to be happy and stand fast, (but not being acted in the Counsel of God to glorify his Name) is the very way they come to be scatter'd and loose their Name. As see <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.8. <hi>And the Lord called Abram and bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him with a Promise of Christ, and said, Get thee cut of thy Country, and from thy Kindred, and from thy Father's House, unto a Land that I will shew thee, and I will make of thee a great Nation; and I will bless thee, and make thy Name great, and thou shalt be a Blessing,</hi> Gen. 12.1, 2. And ministring Angels were sent from the Presence of God to Men, shewing his Mind and Will, as to <hi>Abraham, Isaac, Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> and reached to Men to inspire them with ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Spirits, before the Law, and under the Law, and down to the Gospel of Peace, and had their Services as sent, shewing the Mind of the Spirit through Man's Mouth; and Christ was in the Bosom of the Father in the Beginning, the Spirit of Truth, the Angel of the Lord, and Son, and is with his People to this Day, and hath promised to be with his People to the End of the World; and the Dispensation of Angels glorious, which appeared to the Fathers a second Voice to confirm to do the Will of God: And after the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Angels visited <hi>Abraham,</hi> and he interceeded for <hi>Sodom;</hi> but the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:189133:8"/> number of ten Righteous Persons not being found, the Lord destroyed <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah, Gen.</hi> 18.32. <hi>Then the Lord rained upon</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Gomorrah, <hi>Brimstone and Fire from the Lord out of Heaven,</hi> Gen. 19.24. And after this, <hi>Abraham, Isaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> went through Nations, and sojourned, and planted Truth as they went, and the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to them for their Incouragement, and <hi>Isaac</hi> marry'd <hi>Rebecca;</hi> and a Blessing was in the Seed, and <hi>Jacob</hi> after his Father <hi>Isaac</hi> was blessed; <hi>and God said to Jacob, arise go up to Bethel and dwell there, and make there an Altar to God, that appeared to thee when thou fleddest from the Face of Esau thy Brother,</hi> Gen. 35.1, 2. <hi>and Jacob dwelt in a Land wherein his Father was a Stranger, in the Land of Canaan,</hi> Gen. 37.1. and the Lord was with <hi>Joseph</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and blessed him there, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.8. and after this, the Lord appeared to <hi>Moses</hi> in a burning Bush, he sendeth <hi>Moses</hi> to deliver <hi>Israel,</hi> Exod. 3.7. <hi>the Lord said, I have surely seen the Affliction of my People which are in Egypt, and have heard their Cry, and am come down to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them out of the Hand of the Egyptians, and to bring them up cut of that Land, unto a good Land and a large, unto a Land flowing with Milk and Honey;</hi> and great Signs and Wonders the Lord wrought through <hi>Moses</hi> to bring them out, to praise his Name, and to keep the Lords Rest and Sabbath, and the Passover is instituted, and the First-born of <hi>Egypt</hi> are slain, the <hi>Israelites</hi> are driven out of the Land, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.31. and as the First-born of <hi>Egypt</hi> are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed because of <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s hardness of Heart, and to shew the Lord's great Power; so <hi>the Lord spake unto Moses, saying, Sanctifie to me all the First-born, whatsoever openeth the Womb a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Children of Israel, both of Man and of Beast, it is mine,</hi> Exod. 13.1. and the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of the Passover is commanded; <hi>and they took their Journey from Succoth, and encamped in Etham, in the Edge of the Wilderness; and the Lord went before them by Day in a Pillar of a Cloud, to lead them the way, and by Night in a Pillar of Fire, to go by Day and Night; he took not away the Pillar of a Cloud by Day, nor the Pillar of Fire by Night from before the People,</hi> Exod. 13.20, 22. and this the Lord's Love and settling his Sabbath of Rest, was after the destruction of the old World, and the Confusion of <hi>Babilon</hi>'s Builders, and the Overthrow of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> for Sin; and the World increasing again, and God appeared again, to inform his chosen Generation what Nation they should go to, to shew forth his Power, and was a Guide to <hi>Moses,</hi> and the People, and shewed <hi>Moses</hi> where they should place his Name in Worship, and the first Day for Worship the Lord calls for after this is, to keep his Sabbath of Rest the seventh Day, and fixed <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.23. and after settled into a Commandment, and a Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance put upon it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>For in six Days the Lord made Heaven and Earth, the Sea and all that in them is, and rested the seventh Day, wherefore the Lord blessed the Sabbath Day, and hallowed it;</hi> and on the sixth Day the Lord rained Manna enough for the seventh, and none descended on the seventh Day, according to the Word of the Lord which <hi>Moses</hi> gave to the People, that on the seventh Day there should be none, they should not find it in the Field; and as the Lord gave the People a Day of Rest to keep his Sabbath (not <hi>Jewish</hi>) so the Lord gave them Manna from Heaven, and this Manna was to the visible Eye, and for Bread and Food for the Body; but under the Gospel the Lord descends and rains his Spiritual Manna into the Soul, to nourish the Soul, that it may bring forth Fruit to eternal Life, not abolishing the Day of Rest in which the Father and Son rested, with their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, the Angelical Celestial Bodies, and the Spiritual Male and Female, and hath settled their Rest to the visible Man, and put it into a Command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t, and hath promised to shew Mercy to Thousands of them which love God and keep his Commandments.</p>
            <p>There is a Dispute by a Man of outward Learning, how we shall know the right seventh Day of the Lord's Rest, from <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. to <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. and that it is the same from the raining of Manna to <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. and his Argument is, Records may be lost, and that the Lord's holy Rest is not so much as mentioned from <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. to <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. but all that question the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the seventh Day of the Lord's holy Rest to be a Day before the first Day of the Week on which the Resurrection of Jesus was, I in all Humility desire, that those to whom
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:189133:8"/> this may come, to view the Scriptures set down as afore-mentioned; and see for Mans Wickedness the whole Creation was destroyed, only a Seed preserved, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the Destruction of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah;</hi> and as the World increased again, the Lord did appear to the Fathers <hi>Abraham, Isaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and they went through Nations, and Truth was planted, and the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> called out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in the Red-Sea from the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and Christ was their Spiritual Rock then, and led by the Right-Hand of <hi>Moses,</hi> the Lord giving Victory with his glorious Arm, and the Lord was ever fitting Man for good Works, and that he might come to keep his Rest in Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and a Seed in the faithfulness fixed, and the Lord gave the sign of Circumcision to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that they were to be circumcised in Heart and Ears, and Circumcision a Token of the Covenant between <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Lord, and to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, and the Lord's Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Promise is <hi>to be a God to Abraham and his Seed after him,</hi> (in Christ) <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. so the Lord appeared to perfect Man, and called <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>walk before him, and be thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ch.</hi> 17.1. and when Truth the Lord's Mind was seated in Man's Heart, and Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to call upon the Name of the Lord, then the Lord called for his Sabbath of Holy Rest to be kept Holy, and called for a remembrance to keep it, promising all the Blessings to come upon Obedience and keeping the Lord's holy Rest; and my Call and Satisfaction is from the Lord to keep the seventh Day, the Lord's Rest; and by the first Day of the Week on which the Angel of the Lord descended from Heaven, giving a Resurrection to the Body of Jesus and by the first Day of the Week I know the seventh, and am fully satisfied with the Account the Scriptures give both in the Old Testament and the New, and that it is the right seventh Day, from <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. to <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. and from the raining of Manna to the Commandments; it is, I do firmly believe, the right seventh Day in course from the Creation, being written with the Finger of God, notwithstanding so many over-turnings, as the lower World drowned, and Registers may be lost, as some have in Print signified, and Man mistaken; but pray consider who it is appoints the Day to be kept, and gives the Account at the rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Manna, and in the Commandments; it is he which created the Day and kept it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; and this great Lord knew at the raining of Manna, the right seventh Day from the Creation, and from the raining of Manna to the appearing of <hi>Moses</hi> upon <hi>Mount Sinai;</hi> and this great Lord and Creator hath commanded, <hi>Six Days shalt thou Labour and do all that thou hast to do, but the Seventh Day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God; in it thou shalt do no manner of Work, thou nor thy Son, nor thy Daughter, thy Man-Servant, nor thy Maid-Servant, nor thy Cattel, nor the Stranger that is within thy Gates; for in Six Days the Lord made Heaven and Earth, the Sea, and all that in them is, and rested the Seventh Day, wherefore the Lord blessed the Sabbath Day and hallowed it:</hi> And this great Creator giving the Account, as afore-written, he knew the right Seventh Day in Course from the Creation, and since that Time the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments has born Record, and the Commandments to be observed, not adding nor dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing, and where the Lord hath recorded his Name, the Commandments stand good to this Day; and the Prophets were sent in the Words of God in every Generation, since the Commandments given to proclaim a Blessing upon the People keeping the Sabbath of the Lord thy God holy; and the Record of the Scripture is yet further; <hi>The Lord speak unto Moses saying, speak thou unto the Children of Israel, saying, verily my Sabbaths ye shall keep; for it is a Sign between me and you, throughout your Generations, that ye may know that I am the Lord that doth sanctify you,</hi> Exod. 31.13, 14. <hi>Ye shall keep the Sabbath therefore, for it is holy unto you, every one that defileth it shall surely be put to Death; for whosoever doeth Work therein, that Soul shall be cut off from amongst his People,</hi> Ver. 15. <hi>Six Days may Work be done, but in the seventh is the Sabbath of Rest, holy to the Lord; whosoever doth any Work on the Sabbath Day, he shall surely be put to Death.</hi> And, Ver. 16. <hi>Wherefore the Children of Israel shall keep the Sabbath, to observe the Sabbath throughout their Generation, for a perpertual Covenant,</hi> Ver. 17. <hi>It is a Sign between me and the Children of Israel for ever; for in six Days the Lord made Heaven and Earth,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:189133:9"/> and on the seventh Day he rested and was refreshed.</hi> And, Ver. 18. <hi>He gave unto Moses when he had made an end of communing with him upon Mount Sinai, two Tables of Testimony, Tables of Stone, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the Finger of God;</hi> so this is the Lord's Day of holy Rest, the seventh Day; and the Lord's Command is to keep it holy; and the Lord which created the Days and gave the Day of his Rest as a Sign that he is a God which doth sanctify his People, he did direct <hi>Moses</hi> to the right seventh Day in Course from the Creation to the raining of Manna, and from the rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Manna to the Commandments, and after the Commandments, as afore written, all the Prophets came in the Word of the Lord, and confirmed the keeping the Lord's holy Rest to the Appearance of the great Prophet promised like unto <hi>Moses;</hi> and the Apostles giving an Account of crucifying the Body, they all shew which was the Sabbath, (and the Word through Jesus nor his Disciples did not disanul the keeping the Lord's Rest) and the Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Jesus was on the First Day of the Week, at <hi>the end of the Sabbath, as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to dawn towards the first Day,</hi> Matt. 28.1. <hi>And when the Sabbath was past, they brought sweet Spices, that they might come and anoint the Body,</hi> Mark 16.1, 2. Luke 23.56. <hi>They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned and prepared Spices and Ointments, and rested the Sabbath Day according to the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> Luke 24.1. <hi>Ʋpon the first Day of the Week very early in the Morning, they came to the Sepulchre bringing the Spices which they had prepared,</hi> John 20.1. Thus the Gospel gives an Account both of the First Day of the Week, and the Seventh Day Sabbath, and that the First Day is at the end of the Sabbath; and the Record of all the Prophets is very punctual to keep the Lord's holy Rest, and it is a Day worthy of being kept and observed, when the great Creator hath first set an Example of keeping it himself, a Day before Sin entered the World. And when the Sabbath, and Feasts and Sabbaths are proclaimed to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Israel,</hi> then also the Lord is very great in giving to <hi>Moses</hi> the Distinction of his Rest to be proclaimed from the Sabbaths and Feasts given the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> to be a holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation to afflict their Souls for Sin, and in their Feasts and Sabbaths, to <hi>do no Work in that same Day, for it is a Day of Attonement to make an Attonement for you before the Lord your God,</hi> Levit. 23.28. But these Sabbaths to afflict for Sin are abolished where everlasting Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness is established, and Truth the holy One seated in the Heart; and if the holy One, the Spirit of Truth be obeyed, it will make of Twain one new and living Man; <hi>and the Lord spake yet further unto Moses, saying; speak unto the Children of Israel, and say unto them, concerning the Feasts of the Lord which ye shall proclaim to be holy, Even these are my Feasts,</hi> (the Sabbath and Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sover) <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.1, 2. <hi>Six Days shall Work be done, but the Seventh is the Sabbath of Rest, an holy Convocation, ye shall do no Work therein, it is the Sabbath of the Lord in all your Dwellings.</hi> And ver. 4. the Feast which the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> were to observe in their Seasons, are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed also to afflict their Souls for Sin. And ver. 5. <hi>In the fourteenth Day of the Month, at Even, is the Lord's Passover.</hi> And ver. 9, 10. <hi>The Lord speak unto Moses, saying, Speak unto the Children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye be come into the Land which I shall give unto you, and shall reap the Harvest thereof, then ye shall bring a Sheaf of the First-Fruits of your Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest unto the Priest, and he shall wave the Sheaf before the Lord, to be accepted for you: on the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row after the Sabbath, the Priest shall wave it.</hi> And ver. 22. <hi>When ye reap the Harvest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f your Land, thou shalt not make clean riddance of the Harvest of your Land, the Corners of thy Field, when thou reapest, neither shalt thou gather any Gleanings of thy Harvest, thou shalt leave them unto the Poor, and to the Stranger, I am the Lord your God.</hi> And thus the Lord's Care is to plead for the Poor, that he might bless the Land for their sakes that are poor; that none of his Creation should suffer, and the whole Family of the Earth may be helped. And now observe the Sheaf which the Priest was to wave, was the Morrow after the Sabbath. And it is to be observed again, the Morrow after the Sabbath the Gospel makes out to be the first Day of the Week: <hi>In the end of the Sabbath,</hi> (saith St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> Chap. 28.1.) <hi>as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to Dawn towards the first Day of the Week.</hi> And to the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> as afore-writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the Lord gave many Sabbaths to afflict for Sin, and other Sabbaths to rejoice in (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:189133:9"/> his holy Rest) as see <hi>Levit.</hi> 16.30. and <hi>ch.</hi> 19. the Lord calls for Holiness, and <hi>ch.</hi> 23 40. <hi>Numb.</hi> 29.7. but Sabbaths given the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> to afflict for Sin, the Prophets af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Moses</hi> does not take so much notice of; for Sin remaining, the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> cries out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Sin and their Sabbaths, also of set Feasts and the New-Moon: for Sin remaining, them Sabbaths and set Feasts they became and were seen in the Abomination, as see <hi>Isaiah</hi> 1.11. <hi>to</hi> 16. their Hands <hi>was full of Blood, and they were to be wash'd and made clean, and to turn from the evil of their doings, and cease to do evil, and learn to do well; seek Judgment, relieve the oppressed, judge the Cause of the Fatherless, and plead for the Widow</hi> (not make Widows and Fatherless); <hi>Come now and let us reason together, saith the Lord, though your Sins be as Scarlet, they shall be as White as Snow; though they be Red like Crimson, they shall be as Wool; if ye be willing and obedient, ye shall eat the Good of the Land; but if ye refuse and rebel, ye shall be devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the Sword, for the Mouth of the Lord hath spoken it;</hi> and saith the Prophet, <hi>How is the faithful City become a Harlot, it was full of Judgment, Righteousness lodg'd in it, but now Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers;</hi> for when the Lord sent them to fight his Battles, and to destroy his Enemies, he went before them, giving Power; but when they went forth and destroyed the People as their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, they became Murtherers, and the Lord would not hear their many Prayers in that State; but this does not strike at all at the Lord's holy Rest, the fourth Commandment. Hypocrisie is reproved by the Prophet, and every Prophet: but the Lord's Promises are due to Godliness, keeping the Commandments; and the same Prophet which reproves the Sabbaths of the New Moon, and their set Feasts, calls for keeping the Lord's holy Day and Sabbath, saying, <hi>If thou turn thy Foot away from doing thy pleasure on my holy Day, and call the Sabbath a Delight, the Holy of the Lord honourable, and shall honour him; not doing thine own ways, nor finding thine own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, nor speaking thine own words: then shalt thou delight thy self in the Lord, and I will cause thee to ride upon the high Places of the Earth, and feed thee with the Heritage of Jacob thy Father, for the Mouth of the Lord hath spoken it:</hi> So here the Prophet in the Word of the Lord calls the Sabbath, <hi>The Lord's holy Day, in which the holy of the Lord is to be honoured;</hi> and the Lord in the Ten Commandments calls his Rest, <hi>The Sabbath of the Lord thy God;</hi> and as afore-written, I don't find the Lord's holy Day and Sabbath of Rest is called <hi>Jewish</hi> Sabbath, or <hi>Jewish</hi> seventh Day any where in Scripture, and not such a Word to be found in the Ten Commandments; and as to the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> as afore-written, they had their appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sabbaths and Feasts, one on the tenth Day of the seventh Month a Sabbath, and on the first Day of the seventh Month a Sabbath; <hi>a Memorial of blowing of Trumpets, an holy Conv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; ye shall do no servile Work therein,</hi> (for they were at such times to look into their Souls, and depart from Sin, that it might be a holy Convocation, that their Offerings might be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) <hi>but ye shall offer an Offering made by Fire,</hi> Levit. 23.24, 25. Exod. 19.13. Numb. 29.1. and Levit. 23.32. <hi>In the ninth Day of the Month at Even: from Even to Even shall ye cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate your Sabbath;</hi> and v. 36. <hi>Seven Days ye shall offer an Offering made by Fire unto the Lord;</hi> and when their Offerings in that Dispensation was accepted, the Lord descended Fire from Heaven as a sign of acceptance) but without Holiness the Offerings were not accepted, neither did Fire descend from Heaven; but <hi>Moses,</hi> to distinguish the Sabbaths given to the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> from the Lord's Sabbath of Rest, saith, <hi>Ye shall celebrate the Sabbaths from Evening to Evening;</hi> so these Sabbaths and Feasts of Charity to be given to the Poor, that the Giver might reap the Blessing of such Gifts to the Poor; and the Sabbaths gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the <hi>Jews</hi> to afflict their Souls for Sin may be called the <hi>Jewish</hi> Sabbaths; but these Sabbaths gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the <hi>Jews</hi> to afflict their Souls for Sin, hath no relation to the Lord's holy Rest, which was before Sin entered the World; and as afore-written, <hi>Seven Days ye shall offer an Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made by Fire to the Lord; on the eighth Day shall be an holy Convocation unto you;</hi> and v. 37. <hi>These are the Feasts of the Lord which ye shall proclaim to be holy Convocations, to offer an Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made by Fire unto the Lord, a Burnt-Offering and a Meat-Offering, a Sacrifice and a Drink-Offering, every thing upon his Day;</hi> and these was to be <hi>besides the Sabbath of the Lord, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:189133:10"/> your Gifts, and besides all your Vows, and besides all your Free-Will Offerings, which ye give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord;</hi> and v. 39. <hi>Also in the fifteenth Day of the seventh Month, when ye have gathered in the Fruit of the Land, ye shall keep a Feast to the Lord, seven Days in the Year ye shall celebrate it, in the seventh Month;</hi> but the Lord's Sabbath of holy Rest falling in these seven Days, the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Day is to be kept the holy Rest, and therefore the Record is, ye shall keep the eighth Day, notwithstanding the appointment yearly is but seven Days to be kept, but the Lord's Rest between makes the eighth; <hi>on the first Day shall be a Sabbath, and on the eighth Day shall be a Sabbath;</hi> so here the Law sheweth, as doth the Gospel, which is the first Day and which is the seventh fixed in the Commandments, and the other Sabbaths given to the <hi>Jews</hi> to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict for Sin, are acknowledged to be the Laws and Sabbaths given to the <hi>Jews</hi> in that Dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, that they might be holy, and their Offerings pure, and tried by Fire, and owned by Fire descending from Heaven; and in the Gospel it is the fiery Baptism of the holy Ghost, that purgeth the Soul and burns up the Sin, as all are obedient to its baptizing Power; and Feasts of Charity and good Works stand good for ever, and well pleasing to the Lord, and <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> was to be distinguished from others, <hi>all that are Israelites born shall dwell in Booths seven Days,</hi> Levit. 23.41, 42. And the Lord's Care is over the Poor and Strangers, and a rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and rest from Labour after the gathering in the Corn and Fruits of the Earth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.9. <hi>Seven Weeks shalt thou number unto thee; begin to number the seven Weeks, from such time as thou beginnest to put the Sickle to the Corn;</hi> and v. 10. <hi>Thou shalt keep the Feast of Weeks unto the Lord thy God, with a Tribute of a Free-Will Offering of thine Hand, which thou shalt give unto the Lord thy God, according as the Lord thy God hath blessed thee; and thou shalt rejoice before the Lord thy God, thou and thy Son, and thy Daughter, thy Man-servant, and thy Maid-servant, and the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite that is within thy Gates, and the Stranger, and the Fatherless, and the Widow that are among you;</hi> and v. 12. <hi>Thou shalt remember that thou wast a Bond-man in Egypt;</hi> and v. 13. <hi>Thou shalt abserve the Feast of Tabernacles seven Days,</hi> (a Day for a Week) <hi>after that thou hast gathered in the Corn and the Wine;</hi> and v. 14. <hi>Thou shalt rejoyce in thy Feast, thou and thy Man-servant, and thy Maid-servant, Son, and Daughter, and Levite, the Stranger, the Fatherless and Widow that are within thy Gates;</hi> and v. 18. <hi>Every Man shall give as he is able, according to the Blessing of the Lord thy God which he hath given thee;</hi> so these Feasts the Lord called for, that the Poor might receive the benefit, and he accepts the Offering and Tribute of a Free-Will Offering, as if it was done to him; and <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.28. and <hi>ch.</hi> 15.11. <hi>For the Poor shall never cease out of the Land, therefore I command thee, saying, thou shalt open thine Hand wide unto thy Brother, to thy Poor, and to thy Needy in the Land:</hi> So the Lord's care is over the Poor, the Widow, and Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, and Levite which had no Portion by Inheritance, and the Stranger, that they might have part at the ingathering of the Increase with the Rich, and Acts of Charity and Mercy stands good for ever; thus many Feasts the Lord appointed the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> that they might serve the Needy among them, and reap the Blessings of Increase which the Lord blessed them with, that they might serve the Needy, besides the Lord's Sabbath of holy Rest; and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Jews</hi> had Sabbaths given them to make an Atonement for Sin, and not to rest in Sin, nor leave Calamity upon their Souls, if they were called to the Bar of Divine Justice; and I say as the Gospel makes out the first Day to be at the end of the Sabbath, so doth the Law, <hi>The Priest was to wave a Sheaf before the Lord to be accepted the Morrow after the Sabbath;</hi> and this may tipify ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her Sabbath to be added in the Gospel Dispensation, and so great a work in the Resurrection is worthy of everlasting remembrance, for the Power of God was seen in the Resurrection of the Body, and to wait for the Resurrection of the Seed of Light and Life in each particular, a Blessing is in it; but the first Day is not any where recorded in the Gospel a Sabbath, nor called a Sabbath, but the Lord's Rest is recorded a Sabbath in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of crucifying the Body both in <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> as also in <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>It is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God;</hi> and as afore-written <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.18. <hi>It is written with the Finger of God;</hi> and <hi>Exod.</hi> 35.2. and <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.3. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.14. <hi>It
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:189133:10"/> is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God;</hi> and what Man is that upon a deliberate and second Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, can blot out the seventh Day, the Lord's Sabbath of Rest after six Days of his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating; and it is certain, that the Body of Jesus was raised on the first Day of the Week, and on the same Day, according to the Word of the Lord, met his Disciples, and in the same Word breathed on them and said, <hi>Receive ye the Holy Ghost, as my Father hath sent me, even so send I you;</hi> and after Jesus ascended, the Apostles <hi>were all with one accord in one place,</hi> Acts 2.2, 4. <hi>They were all filled with the Holy Ghost;</hi> and Acts 4.31, 32. <hi>And the multitude of them which believed, were of one Heart and of one Soul,</hi> that is, of one Spirit united in the Faith of the Gospel, <hi>neither said any of them, that ought of the things which he possessed was his own, but they had all things in common;</hi> and thus the great Work and Power of the Gospel went on in the Power of God, and <hi>Acts</hi> 2.44. <hi>All that believed were together, and had all things in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and sold their Possessions and Goods, and parted them to all Men, as every Man had need;</hi> yet notwithstanding all these good Works, the Lord's Sabbath of Rest is to be obeyed, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Commandments and Example of Jesus, who exhorted all to keep the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and kept them himself; and the Apostles waiting to receive the Power, and set an Example of keeping the first Day of the Week, ministring the Spirit, and doing Acts of Mercy, relieving the poor Saints; and it is to the Comfort of all in the Faith of Jesus, to know a feeding of the Word of Life and Gift in the Spirit, which gives Light to the Soul, and where the Holy Ghost is given, it is a Sabbath of Rest, as in the beginning it was when Christ rested with the Father; and the same God which gives Light and Life, and descends the Gift of the Holy Ghost, he did rest the seventh Day, and set the first Example, and their Rest is commanded to be kept holy, and is not abolished; and notwithstanding the Laws of Men does not reach to cut off if they don't keep the seventh Day Sabbath of Rest, yet the Word of God stands good; the Iniquity of the Fathers is visited upon their Children that are found in the Iniquities of their Fathers, and a great cutting off there will be (as is seen in the World there is) till the Lord's Commandments is obeyed, and his holy Rest kept after six Days of their Creation; and to what purpose is it to teach the Children the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God, and say them their selves, and preach many Sermons upon that Subject, and yet not keep that Day at all; the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> had their Sabbaths as afore-written, to afflict for Sin, that they might be purified and sanctified to keep the Lord's holy Rest, and under the Gospel, the Office of Christ which rested with the Father, the Spirit of Truth is regenerating, and purging, and baptizing, and washing away the Sin, and will sanctifie the Soul, which works when the Spirit works with them, that they may be prepared to keep the seventh Day holy; and many Blessings are pronounc'd thro' all the Mouths of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, in keeping the Sabbath; and if they would not hearken to keep the Sabbath, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets shewed the Evil to come, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 17.27. and the Lord hath promised to shew Mercy to Thousands of them that love him and keep his Commandments; but yet visiting the Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the Fathers upon the Children, to the third and fourth Generation of them that hate him, and are found in the Iniquity of their Fathers; for the Soul that sinneth to the end shall die, as saith the Prophets <hi>Jerem.</hi> 31.29. and <hi>Ezek. ch.</hi> 18. <hi>They shall say no more, the Fathers have eaten a sour Grape, and the Childrens Teeth are set on Edge, but every one shall die for his own Iniquity; every Man that eateth the sour Grapes, his Teeth shall be set on Edge;</hi> so he which is the Sabbath-breaker, it is his Iniquity, he is the Sinner to the Third and Fourth Generation, a breaker of the Lord's Commandments. Some argue the Law is changed; but the Answer to that is, God is not changed, and his Word is to be obey'd, and his Commandments kept, which are not abolished by his Word and Finger Writing, for the Commandments were written with the Finger of God; and till the same Finger writes to abolish the Commandment, or any part of them, they stand good: And Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus being a Mouth to the Spirit, and waited for the Word of God which pass'd through him, and Christ spoke in him the Spirit of Truth: And in his first Sermon in the Mount,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:189133:11"/> speaking of the Light to his Disciples, sayeth, <hi>Let your Light so shine,</hi> (so they were drawn to follow him by the Spirit and Word, a Light given them to shine) <hi>before Men, that they may glorify your Father which is in Heaven,</hi> that they may see your good Works, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. to the 20th. <hi>Think not that I am come to destroy the Law, or the Prophets, I am not come to destroy, but to fulfil; for verily I say unto you, till Heaven and Earth pass, one Jot or Tittle shall in no wise pass from the Law till all be fulfill'd: Whosoever therefore shall break one of these least Commandments, and shall teach Men so, he shall be called the least in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> And Chap. 15.3. The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharisees</hi> came to Jesus, saying, <hi>Why do thy Disciples trangress the Tradition of the Elders; for they wash not their Hands when they eat Bread?</hi> But the Power answer'd, <hi>Why do you also transgress the Commandments of God by your Traditions? for God commanded, saying, Honour thy Father and Mother; He that curseth Father or Mother, let him die the Death; but ye say, whosoever shall say to his Father, or Mother, it is a Gift, by whatsoever thou mightest be profited by me, and Honour not his Father or Mother, he shall be free; thus have ye made the Commandments of God of none effect by your Tradition:</hi> And notwithstanding the Lord by his Servants the Prophets, hath promised to make a new Covenant, and write his Laws in the Heart, and put his Spirit in the inward Parts, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. and <hi>John</hi> 6.45. But the Lord by his new Covenant, hath not given away his Honour, nor disannulled the keeping his Sabbath and holy Rest; the great Creator of Heaven and Earth, which created all Things, the Sea, and the Fountains of Water; this the Lord's Rest is to be held in everlasting Remembrance; he is the Fountain of all Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Messengers and Servants, Angels and Seers; who made the great Deep to bow, and the Heavens and the Earth to tremble at his Word: And can Men, upon a serious Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, teach the Commandments to their Children, and say, <hi>Remember to keep the seventh Day holy, and thou shalt do no manner of Work,</hi> and yet do all manner of Work on the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Day, and not keep the Day at all?</p>
            <p>I greatly hope, when these things are consider'd, many will be pleas'd to see for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and yield Obedience to the Lord's Commands, in keeping his Sabbath of Rest holy. I am not pleading for Titles, but for Holiness and Obedience; and this is the positive Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, <hi>Six Days shalt thou labour and do all that thou hast to do, but the Seventh is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God, in all your Dwellings,</hi> Levit. 23.2. But if the Lord is pleas'd to call for any of the Six, or for all the Six, as the Lord did in the set Feasts to be kept yearly; <hi>Seven Sabbaths shall be compleated,</hi> Levit. 23.15. and these seven Sabbaths to begin the Morrow after the Sabbath, and they were to keep the Eighth Day; because the Lord's Rest, I say, fell in between: and these seven Sabbaths may signify, that every Day should be a Sabbath of Holiness to the Soul, a Rest in God, looking over the Work of the Soul every Day, and the Mind staid upon him: but out of Labour every Day Man cannot be, for the Earth is full of Labour; and God which knew Man better than he knew himself, hath called for the Day of his Rest to be kept out of Labour in Holiness, and as aforewrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, if the Lord is pleas'd to call for the six Days to add to his mighty Works, shewing his Power from Generation to Generation; shewing the Work of the Almighty Power both in Creation and Redemption; it is he that is the Saviour and Redeemer, and King, and his mighty Power is seen both in the Dispensation of Angels, and the Ministrations of the Law; and it is his Word in the Prophets, and the Power of God is seen in descending the Power and Spirit, to visit each Particular; and notwithstanding the Dispensation of the Gospel in its Perfection, be prefer'd before the Ministration of the Law, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han Burnt-Offerings and Sacrifices: for the Power of Working in each Particular, which under the Law was only to Witnesses and Leaders, and they to perform the Justice the Law points to; yet that does make the Commandments of God of none effect, nor the First Day the Seventh; and the the Lord's Sabbath of Holy Rest was before Sin or Man was, and is still distinguish'd from all other Sabbaths and Feasts; and the Lord calls for Holiness and Perfection; but Sin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:189133:11"/>
               <hi>Isaiah</hi> is sent to reject their Sabbaths, to afflict for Sin and their set Feasts, as afore-written. <hi>Isaiah</hi> is sent to complain of <hi>Judah;</hi> he upbraideth their Service; he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth to Repentance, saying, <hi>Your new Moons, and your appointed Feasts my Soul hateth, they are a Trouble to me, I am weary to hear them,</hi> Isa. 1.14. Ch. 32.15. And <hi>Isaiah</hi> saw largely the coming of Christ and his Kingdom, the Spirit to be poured from on high: And <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> 3.3. expresses the Power, and Majesty, and Glory of Christ thus: <hi>And he shall sit as a Refiner and Purifier of Silver, and he shall purify the Sons of Levi, and purge them as Gold and Silver, that they may offer to the Lord an Offering in Righteousness; then shall the Offerings of Judah and Jerusalem be pleasant unto the Lord, as in the Days of old, and as in former Years,</hi> faith the Prophet; and they that offer in the Gift of God's Spirit, the baptizing Power of the Holy Ghost and its Fire, this is a pure Offering, and this Fire will consume the Sin, as Fire from Heaven did the outward Offerings, when the Offering was accepted, and this Fiery Baptism purges and makes clean the Soul; and therefore the Sabbaths to afflict the Soul for Sin, are cut off to such as live to God in the Spirit; which was to be the Effect of the outward Offering, that Men should serve God in Light and Perfection, and receive the Peace of everlasting Righteousness; but such as went on in Sin, their Sabbaths to afflict for Sin were Abomination; and their set Feasts and solemn Assemblies, and Offerings not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted: but to the Godly, the Lord, by his Word, through any of his Prophets, never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the keeping of his Rest; nor is there any Day named the Sabbath of the Lord thy God under the Gospel, to be kept in the room of the Seventh; and to obey the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God is to receive Admittance into his Presence, and to observe the Work of his Power through every Instrument, Angel and Seer, in whose Power every Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, Angel, and Seer, came with the Words of God; and without which Power and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit none ought to speak; For God is a Spirit, and they which Worship him must worship in the Voice and Power of the Spirit: <hi>For when the Day of Pentecost was fully come, they were all with one accord, in one Place;</hi> and the Apostles <hi>were filled with the Holy Ghost, and speak with other Tongues, as the Spirit gave them Ʋtterance, the wonderful Works of God,</hi> Acts 2. to the 11th Verse, and Chap. 1.8. But they did not speak till the Spirit gave them ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance, and they were to wait for Power from on High. And Jesus received the Word of God, and Power in that Word, to Commission the Disciples forth in their Ministry; and called his and their Ministry, Preaching the Kingdom of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.43. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.7. <hi>And as ye go, preach, saying, The Kingdom of Heaven is at Hand; heal the Sick, cleanse the Lepers, raise the Dead, cast out Devils, freely ye have received, freely give.</hi> And being ask'd which is the first and great Commandment in the Law? his Answer is, <hi>Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, with all thy Soul, and with all thy Mind; this is the first and great Commandment: and the Second is like unto it, Thou shalt love thy Neighbour as thy self; on these two Commandments hang all the Law and the Prophets,</hi> Mat. 22.36. to 40. Thus Jesus in his Ministry, directeth to love God, and that the love of God is shewed in keeping his Commandments, and not to covet any thing which is thy Neighbours. All good Works are laid up in the Commandments, Charity and Mercy; but that the Remembrance and Day of the Lord's Rest was not to be kept, it was out of Dispute amongst them gather'd to follow Jesus; the Women bring the Spices, <hi>and rested the Sabbath,</hi> Luke 23.56. <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Commandment,</hi> as afore-written; and it is not upon Record, that Jesus, whose Example all Christians are to follow, did any Work but holy Works, as he received Power from God; neither did the Angel of the Lord descend from Heaven, to roul away the Stone on the Seventh Day, but on the First Day, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.7. Neither is the Time of the Passover consistent with the Time of the Sabbath, because the Offering was to be ready a Lamb on the 10th Day of the Month, and the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> went out the 14th out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and notwithstanding Jesus did say, <hi>After two Days is the Feast of the Passover, and the Son of Man is betray'd to be crucify'd:</hi> This does not contradict his rising on the First Day,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:189133:12"/> and after two Days is as many as ye can make Seven, from the Time it is spoken; and this does not alter the Seventh Day Sabbath at all, (to be kept on the First Day of the Week) because the Commandments stand good; neither does the Raising of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> as <hi>John</hi> gives the Account, after Four Days being buried, relate any Thing to the Seventh Day Sabbath, and that the Body was rais'd the Third Day, it is certain on the Sixth Day he was crucify'd and gave up the Ghost, and laid in the Sepulchre, because the Sabbath drew on (at Even) which is one Day, and resting in the Sepulchre the Seventh Day is two Days, and rising on the First Day is the Third Day, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.54. <hi>Mark</hi> 15.42. He was seen 40 Days after, until the Day he was taken up; after he, through the Holy Ghost, had given Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment unto his Apostles, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.2. And the Word from the Holy Ghost was, <hi>Go ye therefore and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost, teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you; and Lo! I am with you always to the End of the World.</hi> And that which continues to the End of the World, is the Word and Spirit of God; the Holy Ghost teaching and baptizing even to the Ends of the Earth. And the Disciples was to wait for the Baptism of the Holy Ghost, the Promise of the Father; <hi>Which,</hi> said Jesus, <hi>ye have heard of me,</hi> Acts 2.1, 33. and Chap. 1.4. And the Promise of the Father is the Word of Power, descending from the Father, through the Son, to the Holy Ghost, descending to visit Men, and baptize the Soul, and teach the Mind to do the Will of the Father: and in which Word the anointing Power of the Holy Ghost, <hi>Jesus went about doing Good,</hi> Acts 10.38. After Jesus was risen on the First Day of the Week, he met his Disciples and performed the Word of the Kingdom; which Word had foretold he should rise the Third Day: And when he met his Disciples on the First Day of the Week, he said, <hi>Peace be unto you; as my Father hath sent me, even so send I you, and when he had said this, he breathed on them, and said, Receive ye the Holy Ghost,</hi> John 20.21. And the Confirmation was great in the Resurrection, shewing, the Word of the Kingdom was with Jesus, according to his anointing in the Dispensation of the Spirit, the Gospel, and its Peace; and the Lord by his Power, and the Example of Jesus and his Disciples after him, hath given a loud Call to Christians in the Ministration of the Spirit, to keep the First Day of the Week in Holiness and good Works; so will the Father have his Honour, and the Son honoured in the Father's Honour. And the Work of the Power observ'd in the Resurrection of Jesus, not disobeying the Commandments, a Remembrance to keep the Lord's holy Rest holy: For he that was the First will be the Last, and his Command stands good, as afore-written; and breaking the Sabbath hath ever brought Judgment upon Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Nations; and as afore-mention'd, the Lord through <hi>Moses,</hi> and all the Prophets, hath called to keep the Seventh Day; and there is no Record that does appoint the blotting out the holy Rest, which was before <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile</hi> by Name was upon the Earth, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding Men call the Seventh Day <hi>Jewish</hi> Seventh Day, for which there is no Record of such a Word in the Ten Commandments; and as to the other Sabbaths given the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Israel,</hi> to afflict their Souls for Sin, they are done away when Christ the Messias, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the everlasting Passoever in Spirit, is come to his Temple to purify and cut down Sin in Man by the Sword of the Spirit, the Word of God, cleansing and purifying both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which hearkens, and hears, and obeys the Law written in the Heart. And the same Prophet which bears Testimony to the Law that should be written in the Heart, and put in the Mind, calls to keep the Sabbath, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.20. to the 25th Verse, and <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.15. And the Lord's many Calls hath been for Holiness, saying, <hi>Be ye holy, for I the Lord thy God am holy;</hi> and in Holiness every Day will be a Sabbath to the Soul; but every Day, as afore-written, Man cannot be from Labour, nor in his Labour wholly have his Mind staid upon God, as he may out of Business: And the Lord, which knew Man better than he knew himself, hath called Man apart to Rest out of Labour, to serve him in Holiness, and to return to his Labour in Holiness of Mind, doing no Evil. And when Jesus came in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:189133:12"/> the Dispensation of Peace, his Message was the Word from God giving Light to the World; and he is sent to put an end to Sin, and to bring in everlasting Righteousness: And he set an Example of Holiness and Obedience, doing the Father's Will; shewing, God <hi>is a Spirit, and they which worship him must worship him in Spirit,</hi> John 4.14. And that the Work of the Spirit should be in his People as believe, as a Well of Water springing up to Eternal Life, <hi>John</hi> 7.39. And if after this manner the Christians under the Gospel, coming up in the Ranks and Degrees of Faith, can begin the Week and end the Week witnessing Peace and Rest to the Soul, giving the Father his Honour of Creation and Rest; and to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Son in the Father, which gives Power to the Son: I greatly hope the others Life-Days will prove a Soul's Peace to them, with their Hands in their Labour, and to Rest with the Lord in the Inward of the Soul, is a perpetual Sabbath to the Mind; but going from Holiness which is in the pure Truth, is going from God and his Divine Law, entring Sin and Satan's dark Power, which leads to everlasting Misery, if continued in in every Dispensation. And Jesus, in the Word of God, is sent to take off the Severities of the Law, the Curse, and Oath, and Burnt-Offerings, he being the Offering for Sin to as many as follow his Example; and the Power of God descends into the Soul, and inflames the Heart in the Love of God, and preserves the Mind; and he observed the Sabbath, and went into the Synagogues, and preached; and Jesus and his Disciples reasoned with the <hi>Jews</hi> out of the Law, and preached the Word of the Gospel Inspiration: And after the Cloud receiv'd the Body of Jesus, his Disciples met on the first Day of the Week, (but never dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own the Seventh Day.) And it is written, <hi>Paul</hi> preach'd unto them ready to depart, and continu'd his Speech until Midnight. And some Dispute, that from Midnight to Midnight may signify from Evening to Evening: but Jesus declaring the Calamities to come, and spake by way of Parable, he distinguished that there is an Even and a Midnight; and his Sayings are these; <hi>Watch ye therefore, for ye know not when the Master of the House cometh, at Even or at Midnight; or at the Cock crowing, or in the Morning; and exhorteth to Watch and Pray,</hi> Mark 13.35. And this sheweth, that Even is not Midnight, as also doth the killing the Passover, and the Lord's going forth at Midnight. And as <hi>Paul</hi> observ'd the First Day of the Week, he also observ'd the Sabbath, and went in among the <hi>Jews</hi> and preached in their Synagogues, <hi>and reasoned with them out of the Scriptures,</hi> Acts. 17.23, 17. But when the Persecution grew so hot, and the <hi>Jews</hi> rejected the Word of God, sent first to them; Then saith the Apostle, <hi>On the Sabbath we went out of the City by a River-side, where Prayer was wont to be made, and we sat down and spake unto the Women which resorted thither,</hi> Acts 16.13. So it is plain, the Apostles kept the Sabbath of Rest, as also met on the First Day of the Week, as Jesus met them after he was risen; and the First Day of the Week implies, there is a Seventh, and if Men may be mistaken in reckoning, because of the Destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the old World, and the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Captivity; yet the Finger of God which writ the Commandments, that Finger cannot be mistaken which gave the Account to <hi>Moses;</hi> and Mens Mistakes does not make more or less than seven Days to the Lord's holy Rest: and the Commandments to be recorded in every habitable Place in the Earth where the Lord records his Name: and the Lord's Mercy is great to shew Man his Duty after so many Falls; and the Destruction of the old World by Water, which is before <hi>Exodus</hi> the 16th, and then at the raining of Manna the Lord entred into Covenant again, and gave the Day of his Rest to be kept holy, and a Remembrance upon it, and who shall blot it out? It is the Lord's Sabbath, not <hi>Jewish</hi> Sabbath, and the Commandments stands good for ever, and the Signs stands good for ever to both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile;</hi> that it is God which sanctifies his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which follows Holiness, and the Lord's Rest is the First Day instituted for Divine Worship; and I understand Divine Worship to be spiritual Worship, and he that was the first will be the Last. And the four Evangelists give an Account, that Jesus and his Disciples, which waited for the immediate Spirit and Word, did frequently go into the Synagogues on
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:189133:13"/> the Sabbath Day, and delivered their Ministry to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Jesus was daily with them,</hi> Luke 22.53. John 18.20. Mark 14.49. and the Disciples after Jesus kept Sabbath with both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> and perswaded them to continue in the Grace of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.42, 45, 46. and saith the Apostles to the <hi>Jews, It was necessary that the Word of God should have been first spoken to you,</hi> (as afore-mentioned) <hi>but seeing ye put it from you, and judge your selves unworthy of everlasting Life; lo we turn to the Gentiles, for so hath the Lord commanded us; and when the Gentiles heard this, they were glad, and glorified the Name of the Lord;</hi> and the Word of the Lord was published throughout all the Region, but the Apostles observed the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath still, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.13. and <hi>ch.</hi> 17.2. <hi>and Paul as his manner was, went in unto them, and three Sabbath Days reasoned with them out of the Scriptures</hi> but did not perswade them not to keep the Sabbath, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.4. <hi>He reasoned in the Synagogue every Sabbath, and perswaded the Jews and the Greeks;</hi> and v. 26. <hi>He spake boldly in the Synagogue;</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> 19.8, 9. <hi>He went into the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, and spake boldly for the space of three Months, disputing and perswading the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Kingdom of God; but when divers were hardened and believed not, but spake evil of that way before the Multitude, he departed from them, and separated the Disciples; disputing dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the School of one</hi> Tyranus; <hi>and this continued two Years; so that all them which dwelt at Asia heard the Words of the Lord, both Jews and Greeks, and God wrought special Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles by the Hands of Paul</hi> (and to God be the Glory of all); and notwithstanding the Apostles did wait for the immediate Word, and were not to speak till the Spirit gave them utterance, and were inured with the Holy Ghost, that is, they were baptized with the Holy Spirit to speak the Word of God, and on whom the Apostles laid their Hands when that Power was upon them, they received the Holy Ghost; that is, they were baptized in Spirit to believe in the Dispensation of the Spirit and Word of God through the Apostles; yet notwithstanding the Apostles kept the Sabbath of Rest, and did not forbid that Day of Worship to neither <hi>Jew</hi> nor <hi>Gentile,</hi> for it is the first Day instituted for Divine Worship, of which the great Creator is the Example, and rested himself. And Jesus having the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Word with him, did observe the Sabbath of Rest, and after many Miracles wrought, <hi>went into his own Country, and his Disciples followed him; and when the Sabbath Day was come, he began to teach in the Synagogue, and many hearing him were astonished, saying, From whence hath this Man these Things? and what Wisdom is this that is given unto him, that even such mighty Works are wrought by his Hands,</hi> Mark 6.2. <hi>ch.</hi> 7.9. and Luke 4.31. and <hi>he came down to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaum, a City of Galilee, and taught them on the Sabbath Day, and they were all astonished at his Doctrine, for his Words was with Power;</hi> and there was some for thrusting him out of the City, v. 29. <hi>They led him to the brow of the Hill whereon the City was built, that they might thrust him down headlong; but he passing through the midst, went his way;</hi> but after they saw the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles wrought, they would have stayed him, that he should not depart from them, (and as Jesus was a Preacher of the Word of God) so v. 43. he saith, <hi>I must preach the Kingdom of God to other Cities, for therefore am I sent; and he preached in the Synagogues of Galilee;</hi> and Luke 5.1. <hi>The People pressed upon him to hear the Word of God.</hi> And the Apostles after the Power ascended, and Jesus was received into the Cloud, the Apostles waited for the descendings of the Power, and met together on the first Day of the Week; but neither Jesus which preached the Kingdom of God, nor his Disciples preaching the Word of the Kingdom, ever in any of their Doctrines disowned the Sabbath of holy Rest, but observed it, and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Kingdom of God in the Synagogues; and as Jesus had given the Word of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to his Disciples, fore-shewing the Resurrection; and when the Word of the Kingdom of God was performed, it was a great confirmation to his Disciples and Followers, which waited for the performance of the Kingdom of God, and they were inspired as they wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to see that Word fulfilled, and received Power to go on in the Work of God, but not to take up a Rest in the Flesh, for that is not the Christian Warfare in neither Law nor Gospel, and they delivered their Testimonies with the hazard of their Lives; under both Law and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:189133:13"/> Gospel, they had Trial of cruel Mockings and Scourgings, of Bonds and Imprisonments, they were stoned, sawn asunder, tempted, slain with the Sword, they wandered about in Sheep-Skins and Goat-Skins, being destitute, tormented, of whom the World was not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, they wandered in Desarts, and in Mountains, and in Dens and Caves of the Earth, <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> 11. So notwithstanding the Work of the Gospel is great, and Jesus and his Disciples their Sufferings were great, in setting an Example of Peace; yet they were not to take up a Rest in the Flesh till the Work in the Spirit was done; and when Nations come to live to and in the Peace of the Gospel, according to their Example, they will honour the Father and Son in one Spirit, as they are one in Spirit; so when Christ has gathered Man into his Spirit, to worship the Father in Spirit and in Truth, then he will present the Church in the Unity of the Spirit to the Father of Spirits; and this Son is the express Image of his Father's Person, the <hi>Spiritual Rock,</hi> Corinth. 10.4. and the Body of Jesus a Vail to the Spirit, and Christ the Lord is within the Veil, and is Spirit and Life, and the Babe a Sign lying in the Manger, and in this glorious Dispensation the Work of the Holy Ghost is seen, the Father through the Son to be Spirit, and none knows the Father but the Son which is Spirit, and they to whom the Son will reveal him; and the Son which reveals the Father is Spirit, as the Father is Spirit, and the Father is the one God, the one Almighty Power both in Creation and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; and Gifts to Men are given of the Holy Ghost, both Father and Son which are Spirit, and draws in to the Work of the Spirit, and in which Spirit <hi>Jesus was anointed with the Holy Ghost,</hi> Acts 10.38. <hi>and went about doing good;</hi> and spake the Words from God as the Spirit gave him utterance; so the Work of Creation, and the Dispensation of Angels before the Law and in the Law, and the Work of the Gospel, and the Examples of Peace is very great, but not put in practice; and he which is the Creator, is the Redeemer, and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier, and Saviour; and to each Work the Lord hath given a Day, first a Day of Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance upon his holy Rest, and through the Works of the Power, the Angel of the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scending, and gave a Resurrection to the Body, a Work which is worthy of remembrance, and Christians are to wait for Light and Life which the Power gives, and each particular to wait for a Resurrection in that Seed which gives Life, to hear the Voice of God speaking in their Souls (as it did in Jesus,) that they may be the Disciples of Christ, in the Power and Spirit which hath called them to live in the Truth and Peace of the Gospel; for as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel is Peace, so the Severities of the Law is taken off to them which live in Christ, and are disciplin'd under the Gospel Spirit, according to the Examples of Jesus and the Disciples, and Laws and Oaths, and Sword and Force which was under the Law, are taken off under the Gospel, and to serve the Lord with Holyness and Peace, and Long-suffering till the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel is established through Nations, in that Peace which humbles Christians, and teaches them to do the Will of God in his Season; and the seventh Day, as afore-mentioned, hath never been disannull'd by the same Finger of Power which writ the Commandments, nor hath it been disannull'd through Jesus, nor his Disciples which preached the Word of God; the Word of the Kingdom, and the Father the Creator of all Things ought to be obeyed, and his Commandments kept from Generation to Generation, and through Nations where the Lord's Name is recorded; and to teach the Children to say the Ten Commandments, and to say, <hi>Remember to keep the seventh Day holy, it is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God,</hi> and yet not keep it at all, and so say and not do to the end of their Days, through Generations and Nations; and for these Things, disobeying the Commandments, and not living in the Peace of the Gospel, shewing Love to Neighbours, the Lord's Controversie is with Nations, and this Nation in particular, because of its great Light, and many have been and still are in the profession of the Light, but not living in the Peace of the Gospel, nor to the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, in shewing Love to Neighbours, the Light of many is and will be made dark, and the Judgment will come heavy to those that are not pitiful and merciful; and the Example of the Apostles is to do good Works; they met on the first Day of the Week, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:189133:14"/>
               <hi>gave Orders to the Churches of Galatia, upon the first Day of the Week, let every one of you lay up by him in Store, as God hath prospered him, that there be no gathering when I come,</hi> 1 Cor. 16.2. <hi>and they did continue daily with one accord in the Temple, and breaking Bread from House to House,</hi> (or at Home) <hi>did eat their Meat with gladness and singleness of Heart, praising God, and having fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with all the People, and the Lord added to the Church such as should be saved,</hi> Acts 2.46, 47. and the Lord is the same to this Day, adding to the Church such as live in the Truth; and it is recorded, <hi>John was in the Spirit on the Lord's Day;</hi> and some will have it, the first Day is meant the Lord's Day, but that part of Scripture does not say, whether it were the first Day or the seventh Day which <hi>John</hi> was in the Spirit, but the Voice was from him which is <hi>the first and the last,</hi> Revel. 1.10, 11. and he that is the first and will be the last, hath called the seventh Day his holy Day; and this <hi>John</hi> saw, the <hi>Dragon was wroth with the Woman, and went to make War with the remnant of her Seed, which kept the Commandments of God, and have the Testimony of Jesus Christ,</hi> ch. 12.17. and ch. 14.12, 7. <hi>Here is the patience of the Saints, here are they that keep the Commandments of God and the Faith of Jesus;</hi> and the loud Voice of the Angel which had the <hi>everlasting Gospel to preach unto them that dwell on the Earth, and to every Nation, and Kindred, and Tongue, and People is, Fear God and give Glory to him, for the Hour of his Judgments is come, and worship him that made Heaven and Earth, and the Sea, and the Fountains of Waters;</hi> and after this Description of the Angel, to worship him that made Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, there is reason to believe, it was the Lord's Rest that <hi>John</hi> was in the Spirit, the seventh Day, since the loud Cry of the Angel which had the everlasting Gospel to preach, is to give <hi>worship to him which made Heaven and Earth, and the Sea, and the Fountains of Waters,</hi> which Worship is due to none but the Almighty, which bears Rule by his invisible Power over the Kingdoms of Men which dwell upon the Earth; and as the Lord by Wisdom made the Worlds, he hath been so merciful to call Man and Woman to keep their Rest, and Rest for the Cattle, that there might be a true Rest throughout the earthly Part of Men; and to be holy, that they may receive the Fruits of Holiness, and shew Mercy to all, and the Holy Seed is ever at Rest in the Spirit, when God which is their Light is glorified; the Lord hath enlighten'd Man's Dust, and beautified it with their own Image and Likeness, to be a Light in Man, that Man may work the Work of the Day as the Spirit works in him, the Spiritual Male and Female never consents to Sin, but reproves Sin in the inward Man; and well would it be if all that own the Name Christian, and record his Name, and also own the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments should be kept, if they were obedient to the peaceable Faith they profess, it would give a great Light in the World, and the Days are to be called as the Lord hath called them, as First, Second and Third, Fourth and Fifth, Sixth and Seventh Day, and because the Days are not called as the Lord hath called them, therefore Multitudes in every Nation are to seek to know the Holy Rest, but call it as the Heathens have given it a Name <hi>Saturday,</hi> and many neither keep the seventh nor the first, according to the Works of the Power both in Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Redemption; and if the Days were called as the Lord hath called them, it might bring a Sobriety over many more, to see the great Works of Creation, and to look into the Beauty of every Leaf and Plant of the Field, and for Man to see his own nothingness, and what he is in God is his great Advantage.</p>
            <p>There is some which observe the Evening and the Morning is not so much as mentioned to the seventh Day, and whether the beginning and end of the seventh be the same with the other six; and he seems to question, whether the seventh takes its entrance at Sun-set the sixth Day? I have only this to say, as the Scripture gives the Record, the Evening and the Morning is for six Days, and the seventh hath its Time and Light in course, or else the first Day again must be out of its course, and then there is no knowing the seventh part of Time; and it may be seen, the seventh begins and ends like the other six; and there is a Question proposed, Whether the Lord sanctified the whole Day, or a part for Worship? But the Scriptures are plain, <hi>God blessed the seventh Day and sanctified it, because in it he had rest;</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:189133:14"/> and to me it is most sure, that God which created all things, did begin and end the seventh according to his own appointment of the other six for it has its Evening and its Morning; and some in contradiction to the Sabbath of Rest, taking its entrance at the setting of the Sun on the sixth Day, they observe there was no Sun for three Days, which is true; but if they please to observe again, there was a Sun, Moon and Stars created the fourth Day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord's Rest, which is no Argument the Sabbath may not begin at Sun-set at the end of the sixth Day; and notwithstanding for three Days the Evening is not distinguished by the setting of the Sun, yet it is said to be the Evening and Morning is the first, and second, and third Day, and Sun and Moon and Stars was after made, and the <hi>two great Lights set in the Firmament of Heaven, to give Light upon the Earth, and to divide the Day from the Night, and for Signs and for Seasons, and for Days and Years;</hi> but the Evening, at the going down of the Sun, comes to be the better known to poor Mortals, after the Sun is set in the Firmament of Heaven, not but it was the Evening and the Morning, concludes the Day before the Sun was set in the Firmament, and the Evening was, and the Morning was and is recorded the Day, but the Sun in its appearance, rising and setting, distinguish the Mid-day and Evening bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than for three Days, when there was no Sun appeared, to shew the distinction of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening and Morning, and Mid-day, as the Sun passeth through the Circuit of Heaven; and that ye may be assured the Evening and the Morning compleats the Day, as well as when there was a Sun, it is so mentioned for six Days, and the Evening and the Morning is the Rule to know the Day in every Climate and habitable Place of the Earth, where the Lord recorded his Name; and the Sun sheweth (as afore-written) a Noon or Mid-day, and Afternoon, and shews its drawing to the West, in its Hours and Time, the Day being long or short in every Climate; and the Question is put by a Master of Art, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was Day-light all at one Minute all over the World? To which the Scriptures are silent, and many Places were not found out to give an Account of; and it may be seen, the Day breaks gradually, and the Clouds disappear, and the Morning grows brighter and brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the Night Stars disappear, and the bright Star of the Morning appears, till the Sun with its Glory over-shadows that Star with its bright Beams; and there is degrees of disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the Curtains of Heaven, and the rising of the Morning and its Light; and this is plain, and a Rule set down, and in every habitable place of the Earth, the Evening and the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are the recorded Day, and Men are to be informed by the Power of God and his Signs in the Heavens what by Learning they have not attained to; but Men nor Angels have not been sent to turn the seventh Day into the first, and so turn the Rest of the Lord thy God, and the Worship due to his Rest out, and not keep it at all; and this Master of Art declares, he will not undertake to say what shall become of the seventh Day; that of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, the seventh Day after six of Labour, (and yet every where in his printed Book argues against keeping the seventh Day, calling it <hi>Jewish Weekly Sabbath</hi>) which I am (saith he) fain to mention so often in defence of my self and others, because where you find any to mention, that the Weekly Sabbath or Seventh Day Sabbath, meaning that of the fourth Commandment, is not abolished, you presently catch at it, as if I spoke it of the seventh Day, that of the <hi>Jews,</hi> from the first raining of Manna; whereas you know, that even those who thus speak, do constantly maintain, that the <hi>Jews</hi> seventh Day was exchanged for the Lord's Day, which is a Weekly Sabbath, as well as that of the <hi>Jews</hi> (saith he); to this it is often already said, The Lord's Sabbath of Holy Rest was before <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile</hi> by Name was; and at the first raining of Manna it was the Lord's holy Rest, not <hi>Jewish</hi> Sabbath; and all that come to be holy, have a Call into that Rest, and it was given the Church to keep as the Lord's holy Rest, and is the same with the fourth Commandment; and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> gives the Account, it was <hi>the Lord came down upon Mount Sinai, and madest known unto them his holy Sabbath, and gave them Bread from Heaven for their Hunger, and broughtest forth Water out of the Rock for their Thirst, and promised them that they should go in to to possess the Land which thou
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:189133:15"/> hadst sworn to give them,</hi> Nehem. 9.13. and when they were entered the Land, <hi>If the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Land bring Ware or any Victuals on the Sabbath Day to sell, that we would not buy it of them on the Sabbath,</hi> ch. 10.30, 31. and the Rulers and People entered into a Covenant and Oath, <hi>to walk in God's Ways, and to observe and do all the Commandments and his Statutes, and that we will not give our Daughters to the People of the Land, nor take their Daughters for our Sons;</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> makes a distinction between the Lord's Sabbath and the other Sabbath, in giving such a particular Charge and holy Care to observe the Lord's Sabbath of Rest; and all the Prophets, after <hi>Moses,</hi> doth proclaim the Lord's Sabbath before all other Sabbaths, and saith, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.15. <hi>to</hi> 22. <hi>In those Days saw I in Judah some treading Wine-Presses on the Sabbath, and bringing in Sheaves, and lading Asses; as also Wine, Grapes and Figs, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Burdens, which they brought in to Jerusalem on the Sabbath Day; and I testified against them in the Day wherein they sold Victuals. There dwelt Men of Tire therein, which brought Fish and all manner of Ware, and sold on the Sabbath unto the Children of Judah and in Jerusalem. Then I contended with the Nobles of Judah, and said, What evil thing is this that ye do, and profane the Sabbath Day; did not your Fathers thus, and did not our God bring all this Evil upon us, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this City? yet ye bring more Wrath upon Israel by profaning the Sabbath. And it came to pass that when the Gates of Jerusalem began to be dark before the Sabbath, I commanded the Gates should be shut, and I charged they should not be opened till after the Sabbath; and some of my Servants set I at the Gates, that there should no Burden be brought in on the Sabbath Day. So the Merchants and Sellers of all kind of Ware lodged without Jerusalem once or twice; then I testified against them and commanded the Levites they should cleanse themselves, and come and keep the Gates and sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the Sabbath;</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the Prophet gives in his Testimony in the Word of the Lord for keeping the Sabbath, saying, <hi>Thus saith the Lord unto me, Go and stand in the Gates of the Children of the People, whereby the Kings of Judah come in, and by which they go out, and in all the Gates of Jerusalem, and say unto them, Hear ye the Word of the Lord, ye Kings of Judah, and all the Inhabitants of Jerusalem that enter in by these Gates, thus saith the Lord, Take heed to your selves, and bear no Burthen on the Sabbath Day, nor bring in by the Gates of Jerusalem, neither car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry forth a Burthen out of your Houses on the Sabbath Day, as I commanded your Fathers, but they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed not, neither inclined their Ear, but made their Neck stiff, that they might not hear nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Instructions,</hi> (so they were to take heed to themselves that they did not any of these things, which would lead in Judgments and the violence of War upon them) <hi>and it shall come to pass, if ye diligently hearken unto me, saith the Lord, to bring in no Burthen through the Gates of the City on the Sabbath Day, but hollow the Sabbath Day to do no Work therein, then shall there enter into the Gates of the City, Kings and Princes sitting upon the Throne of David, riding in Chariots and on Horses, they and their Princes, the Men of Judah, and the Inhabitants of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem, and this City shall remain for ever, but if ye will not hearken to me, to hallow the Sabbath Day, and not to bear a Burthen even entering in at the Gates of Jerusalem on the Sabbath Day, then will I kindle a Fire in the Gates thereof, and it shall devour the Palaces, and it shall not be quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,</hi> Chap. 17.19. to the end of the Chapter; and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> repeats the Lord's Complaint a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Israel,</hi> the Rulers Rebellion, and saith the Lord by the Mouth of <hi>Ezekiel, I gave them my Statutes, and shewed them my Judgments, which if a Man do, he shall even live in them; moreover I gave them my Sabbaths, to be a Sign between me and them; but the House of Israel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled against me in the Wilderness; they walked not in my Statutes, and they despised my Judgments, which if a Man do he shall even live in them; and my Sabbath they greatly polluted: Then I said, I would pour out my Fury upon them in the Wilderness to consume them, but I wrought for my Names sake, that it should not be polluted before the Heathen, in whose sight I brought them out; yet also I lifted up my Hand to them in the Wilderness, that I would not bring them into the Land which I had given them, flowing with Milk and Honey, which is the Glory of all Lands; because they despised my Judgments, and walked not in my Statutes, but polluted my Sabbaths, for their Hearts went af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Idols; nevertheless mine Eye spared them from destroying them, neither did I make an end
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:189133:15"/> of them in the Wilderness: But I said to their Children in the Wilderness, Walk ye not in the Statutes of your Fathers, neither observe their Judgments, nor defile your selves with their Idols; I am the Lord your God, keep my Judgments and do them, and hallow my Sabbaths; and they shall be a Sign between me and you, that ye may know that I am the Lord your God; notwithstanding the Children rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me, they walked not in my Statutes, neither kept my Judgments to do them, which if a Man do, he shall even live in them; they polluted my Sabbaths: then I said, I would pour forth my Fury upon them, to accomplish my Anger against them in the Wilderness, because they had not executed my Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and had polluted my Sabbaths, and their Eyes were after their Fathers Idols,</hi> Ezek. 20.12. to 25. Thus the Prophets were all sent in the Word of the Lord one after another, to testify both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Prince and People that break his Covenant; and <hi>Isaiah</hi> in the Word of the Lord saith, <hi>Keep ye Judgment and do Justice, for my Salvation is near to come, and my Righteousness to be reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; blessed is the Man that doeth this, and the Son of Man that layeth hold on it, that keepeth the Sabbath from polluting it, and keepeth his Hands from doing any evil. Neither let the Son of the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that hath joined himself to the Lord, speak, saying, The Lord hath utterly separated me from his People; neither let the Eunuch say, Behold, I am a dry Tree; for thus saith the Lord unto the Eunuch that keep my Sabbaths, and choose the Things that please me, and take hold of my Covenant, even to them will I give in mine House, and within my Walls, a Place and a Name better than of Sons and Daughters; I will give them an everlasting Name that shall not be cut off. Also the Sons of the Stranger that join themselves to the Lord, to serve him, and to love the Name of the Lord, to be his Servants, every one that keepeth the Sabbath from polluting it, and taketh hold on my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, even them will I bring to my holy Mountain, and make them joyful in my House of Prayer,</hi> Isaiah 56.1 to 7. So here the Scripture sheweth, none is shut out from the Lord, and his People that keep his Sabbath holy, the seventh Day after six of Labour, and them that keep the Lord's Sabbath, not doing any Evil, are joined to the Lord in Worship, and he has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to give them a Name better than of Sons and Daughters, and bring them to his holy Mountain; and all that appear in the Gift of his Presence they know his holy Mountain; and when the Lord's Presence visits them they know a Peace-Offering; but from <hi>Genesis</hi> to the last Chapter of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> there is not any Scripture forbids the keeping the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God; and he that was the first, will be the last, and the Day of his Rest will stand for ever among the Angelical Spirits; and he that createth and governs the World and all Things by his mighty Power, will gain the Victory over the World and its Wars; and the Lord by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> sheweth a Catalogue of <hi>Jerusalems</hi> Sins, which were in her before the Judgments came upon her, and proved their Ruin, and saith the Prophet, <hi>Behold, the Princes of Israel every one were in thee to their power to shed Blood; in thee have they set light by Father and Mother; in the midst of thee have they dealt by Oppressi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n with the Stranger; in thee have they vexed the Fatherless and the Widow; thou hast despised my holy Things, and hast prophan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Sabbaths; in thee are Men that carry Tales to shed Blood; in thee they eat upon the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; in the midst of thee they commit Lewdness; in thee they discover their Fathers nakedness; in thee have they humbled her that was set apart for Pollution; and one hath committed Abomination with his Neighbour's Wife, and another hath lewdly-defiled his Daughter-in-Law, and another in thee hath humbled his Sister, his Father's Daughter; in thee have they taken Gifts to shed Blood; thou hast greedily gained of thy Neighbour; therefore thus saith the Lord God, because ye are all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Dross, behold therefore I will gather you into the midst of Jerusalem, as they gather Silver, and Brass, and Iron, and Lead, and Tin, into the midst of the Furnace, to blow the Fire upon it, to melt it; so will I gather you in mine Anger and in my Fury, and I will leave you there and melt you; yea, I will gather you and blow upon you in the Fire of my Wrath, and ye shall he melted in the midst thereof, and ye shall know that I the Lord have poured out my Fury upon you,</hi> Ezek. 22.6. to the 12 ver. and from 19 to 23. and ver. 27. <hi>Her Princes in the midst thereof are like Wolves ravening the Prey to shed Blood, and to destroy Souls to get dishonest gain; and her Prophets had daubed them with untempered Morter, seeing Vanity, and divining Lies unto them, saying, Thus saith
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:189133:16"/> the Lord, when the Lord hath not spoken;</hi> and the Prophets which so daub with their untem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered Morter, they are Murderers of Souls, of both Prince and People; ver. 29. <hi>The People of the Land have used Oppression, and exercised Robbery, and have vexed the Poor and Needy; yea, they have oppressed the Stranger wrongfully; and I sought for a Man among them that should make up the Hedge, and stand in the Gap before me for the Land, that I should not destroy it, but I found none; therefore have I poured out mine Indignation upon them, I have consumed them with the Fire of my Wrath, their own Ways have I recompenc'd upon their Heads, saith the Lord;</hi> and for these Sins remaining and reigning, the Anger of the Lord is poured forth from Generation to Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; and when the Measure is full in every Generation, and the Iniquity is at the heighth, as it now makes its appearance, for which the Lord is visiting the World with his Judgments; and the Lord hath ever shewed his displeasure for Sin and breaking his Sabbath, for the Lord will be glorified in all his Works; and many Threatnings are to them which keep not his Covenant, as many are the Blessings promised to them that love God, and keep his Commandments of Mercy and Peace; and saith the Lord by <hi>Moses, If ye walk in my Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and keep my Commandments and do them, then will I give you Rain in due season, and the Land shall yield her Increase, and the Trees of the Field shall yield their Fruit, and your Threshing shall reach unto the Vintage, and the Vintage shall reach unto the sowing Time; and ye shall eat Bread to the full, and dwell in your Land safely, and I will give you peace in the Land, and ye shall lie down, and none shall make you afraid; and I will rid evil Beasts out of the Land, neither shall the Sword go through the Land. I will have respect unto you, and make you fruitful, and multiply you, and establish my Covenant with you, and ye shall eat old store, and bring forth the old because of the new; and I will set my Tabernacle amongst you, and my Soul shall not abhor you, and I will walk among y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u, and will be your God, and ye shall be my People; but if ye will not hearken unto me, and will not do all these Commandments; and if ye will despise my Statutes, if your Souts abhor my Judgments, so that ye will not do all my Commandments, but that ye break my Covenant; I also will do this unto you, I will even appoint over you Terror, Consumption and the burning Ague; and ye shall sow your Seed in vain, for your Enemies shall eat it; and I will set my Face against you, and ye shall be slain before your Enemies, they that hate you shall reign over you; and if ye will not for all this hearken unto me, then I will punish you seven times more for your Sins; and I will break the Pride of your Power; and I will make your Heavens as Iron, and your Earth as Brass, and your Strength shall be spent in vain; for your Land shall not yield her Increase, neither shall the Trees of the Land yield their Fruits; and if ye will walk contrary unto me, and will not hearken unto me, I will bring seven times more Plagues upon you, according to your Sins; and I will bring a Sword upon you that shall avenge the Quarrel of my Covenant,</hi> Levit. 26. from the 3d to the 26th ver. <hi>and if ye will not for all this hearken unto me, but walk contrary unto me, then will I walk contrary unto you also in Fury; and I, even I, will chastise you seven times for your Sins;</hi> and <hi>Moses</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wherein the Blessings are to the obedient, and the Judgments to the disobedient that keep not the Commandments of God; and the Judgments appointed for Sin will be poured forth under the Gospel Dispensation (as under the Law), when the Measure of Iniquity is full, it will come even to this Generation, the Judgments stands at the Door and is entering our Land, and this our Land will enjoy her Sabbaths as long as it lieth desolate, and ye be in your Enemies Land (as it was said to the Children of <hi>Israel</hi>), then shall the Land rest and enjoy her Sabbaths, as long as it lieth desolate it shall rest, because it does not rest in your Sabbaths: for not only was the Desolation to come upon the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> which liv'd after the Flesh, but upon every Generation will the Desolations come, which obey not the Commandments of God, and disobey the Covenant of Light; which Commandments and Covenant of Light is perpetual, whilst the Sun and Moon endures; for God, which gave the Commandments, is the Light, and will continue the Light to all that obey the Voice: and not one Word in the Commandments (as afore written) is contrary to the Peace of the Gospel, and its Power and good Spirit teaching Obedience in the Power of the Holy Ghost,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:189133:16"/> which gives a Visitation in the Spirit, descended down of both Father and Son, to inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en each Particular, that waits for that Spirit of the Son which leads to the Father, and gives entrance into the Kingdom of Light, which leads to Life; and as the Soul is beautified with Holiness, Christ will raign in his Kingdom of Peace, and till People and Nations come to keep the first Step in Religious Worship, of which the Lord hath set the Example, and hath put it into a Command, if Men will not take the great Creator for an Example, and join with him in Worship, then the Sword will not depart such a Nation, and they will be yet punished for their Iniquities. And <hi>Isaiah,</hi> which had a great Foresight of Christ's Kingdom, and was made a Minister of Christ, and spake when the Spirit was upon him: and after he had reproved the Rulers for keeping the Sabbath of the New Moon and set Feasts, their Sin remaining, and their Hands were full of Blood; and for that Cause their Sins remaining, their Oblation was an Abomination, and rejected; and yet, after such Reproofs to them for such Assemblies, the same Prophet calls to the rising Generations, in the Word of the Lord, to keep the Lord's Sabbath, and join to the Lord, and gives Incouragement; and that the Eunuch, nor the Sons of the Stranger shall not be rejected, but received into the Church, and in Holiness joined to the Lord; and under the Gospel, <hi>Without Holiness none can see the Lord.</hi> And all Nations are to bring their Offerings to the new and spiritual <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> were God and the Lamb are the Temple of it, and the Light of the Holy City to the Pure in Heart, that eye Peace in all its Circumstances: and to be clear of the Blood of all Nations, which live carelesly, and in the Bitterness one to another, till their Measure of Iniquity is full, and then the Lord will send his Sword; and when the Sword of the Lord enters the Land and his fierce Anger appears, he hath many ways to destroy, and many sorts of Armies to call for, which Men can't contend with: notwithstanding it be but Flies and Worms, and the poor creeping Caterpillars, or the biting Serpent; there is no hiding from his Presence: <hi>The Lord God of Hosts is he that toucheth the Land and it shall melt, and all that dwell therein shall mourn: It is he that buildeth his Stories in the Heavens, and hath founded his Troops in the Earth; he that calleth for the Waters of the Sea, and poureth them out upon the Face of the Earth; the Lord is his Name,</hi> Amos 9.5, 6. and Jer. 29.17. And the Lord will distress them which distress <hi>Sion,</hi> and will gather his <hi>Israel,</hi> (notwithstanding <hi>Israel,</hi> after the Flesh) is to be sifted as in a Sive, that the pure Seed and Grain may appear to worship him, and keep his Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath: and the Lord's Promise is, not one Grain the less shall not fall upon the Earth of this pure Seed; but this Promise is not to the Sinners: <hi>All the Sinners of my People shall die by the Sword, which say, The Evil shall not overtake nor prevent us: In that Day will I raise up the Tabernacle of David that is fallen, and close up the Breaches thereof, and I will raise up his Ruins, and will build it, as in Days of old, that they may possess the Remnant of Edom; and all the Heathen which are called by my Name, saith the Lord of Hosts, that doeth this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the Lord hath promised to bring again the Captivity of his People <hi>Israel; And I will plant them upon their Land, and they shall no more be pulled up out of their Land which I have given them, saith the Lord thy God,</hi> Amos 9.9. to the end of the Chapter. Thus Man's planting will be brought to nought, and their Vine and Vineyard destroyed, till the Lord of Host raign in <hi>Sion,</hi> and Christ's Kingdom of Peace is established: <hi>And the Lion come to lie down with the Lamb, and the Wolf also shall dwell with the Lamb, and the Leopard shall lie down with the Kid; and the Calf, and the young Lion, and the Fatling together, and a little Child shall lead them; and the Cow and the Bear shall feed their young ones, shall lie down together; and the Lion shall eat Straw like the Ox, and the sucking Child play on the Hole of the Asp; and the weaned Child shall put his Hand on the Cockatrice Den. They shall not hurt nor destroy in all my holy Mountain; for the Earth shall be full of the Knowledge of the Lord, as the Waters cover the Sea,</hi> Isa, 11.6. to Verse 10. and Chap. 65.25. Thus the Prophet having a great Sight of the peaceable King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Christ, he begins and ends with Peace; shewing, the angry, and fierce, and poison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Nature is done away in the Peace of Christ's Kingdom. And after the Prophet, in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:189133:17"/> Word of the Lord, had reproved the Rulers and People in a shew of Worship, when their Hands were full of Blood, and in that State the Lord would not hear their Prayer, <hi>Isa.</hi> 1.15. and Chap. 1.4. the Prophet prophesieth the further coming of Christ's Kingdom; he exhorteth to Fear, because of the powerful Effects of God's Majesty; and in the Word which he saw concerning <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jerusalem: And it shall come to pass in the last Days, that the Mountain of the Lord's House shall be established in the top of the Mountains, and shall be exalted above the Hills, and all Nations shall flow unto it: And many People shall go and say, Come ye, and let us go up to the Mountain of the God of Jacob, and he will teach us of his Ways, and we will walk in his Paths: for out of Sion shall go forth the Law, and the Word of the Lord from Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. And he shall judge among the Nations, and shall rebuke many People, and they shall beat their Swords into Plow-shears, and their Spears into Pruning Hooks; Nation shall not lift up Sword against Nation, neither shall they learn War any more: O House of Jacob come ye, and let us walk in the Light of the Lord,</hi> as saith the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> in the Word of the Lord, <hi>Chap</hi> 4. to <hi>Ver.</hi> 4. In which Word there is Majesty, and Majesty is in the Spirit sent forth to both the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and People, to reprove their Evils, and to give right Judgment to rule the People in that Word: for Majesty is not in the bodily Presence which is clothed with Flesh, but the spiritual Presence which was with <hi>Moses, Exod.</hi> 33.14. Majesty is the pure Grace which represents the Person of God by his spiritual Voice in Man, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.15. and there is Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty in them Words, and out of this Grace Mens Words are nothing of force to savour the earthly part of Men to Salvation; and when the Words are savour'd with Grace, there is a meek Majesty appears from the one Lord God, the good Spirit, the Holy Ghost, both Father and Son, one in Spirit, giving Life and Light to Men, and therefore are the one God which comes in their glorious Persons, shining in their glorious Apparel, and the Saints in Light they behold them; and when ye hear the Majesty on high, pray don't ye go on in the opposition, as some present upon the Earth have done, when the Word was made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest in its Time to them. And now a further Manifestation is given in the Gospel, which is, <hi>Peace and Good-Will to all Men,</hi> waiting for the Grace and good Spirit; and shewing the Sabbath of holy Rest is in Christ under both the Law and Gospel; and that the Lord's Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath of holy Rest doth not end in Christ, the Sabbath is in Christ which rested with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, after six Days of their Creation; and that prepared Body, Jesus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> a Sign of the Substance within the Veil, and a blessed Sign too, shewing forth the Works of the Spirit to the obedient Soul, waiting for the Consolation of <hi>Israel,</hi> and for the coming of that Glory and true Rest to the World, that Nations may rest in Peace. But Oh! how dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful it is, almost all Nations are in Blood and Confusion, to the Shame of Christianity; which is, Love and Meekness, and Good-Works, and Long-sufferings, and Patience; for the Life of Man is but as a Span long, and in that space of Time, to shew Mercy, and do Justice; for all must appear before the great Judge of all the Earth. And this Word came to me the 30th Day of the 10th Month 1715-6. <q>The Lord will weigh the Nations as in Scales, and the Hills and the Mountains shall know that he hath created the Valeys, as also the highest Mountain and Hill; and he will thresh the Mountains and Hills, and preserve the Valleys by his Power; and the Valleys shall bear its Increase when the Hills are barren; and my Sabbath of Rest I will require at their Hands, which would destroys the Valleys, and the Valleys shall be perpetual in my Rest, when the high Hills are destroyed with the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Israel,</hi> (after the Flesh); but the Valleys shall bear their Increase to my Glory, and stand in my Power and Church, and be defended by my Arm and Strength, saith the Lord.</q> And as aforewritten, <hi>the Peace of the Law is in keeping the Commandments and live,</hi> (as saith the Gospel) and Acts of Charity, and to shew Mercy and Love to Neighbours is to be fulfilled, and is in the Peace of both Law and Gospel, and to them which are called and believe, they should live to the Peace of the Christian Faith, and shew Love to Neighbours, and suffer for the Faith, according to the Examples of the Gospel; the Severities of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:189133:17"/> Law is useless to such as live in the suffering Faith of a Christian, which is to seek the good of all Nations; but Disobedience to the Gospel leads into the Severities and Judgments of the Law, and the Judgments of God also; Transgressor against Transgressor; and the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God are against Sin, under both the Law and Gospel, as the opening of the seven Seals in the <hi>Revelations</hi> of the Angel to <hi>John</hi> sheweth; and to enter into the Severities of the Law, such must partake of the Judgments of God against Sin, for their Disobedience to both the Law and Gospel, which saith, <hi>Keep the Commandments and live;</hi> and Christ's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the Mount, through that ever blessed Mouth <hi>Jesus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> that is, Christ the Lord, the Spirit of Truth, spake in him, and as he delivered his Ministry saith, <hi>One jot or one tittle shall in no wise pass from the Law till all be fulfilled,</hi> Mat. 5.17. and them which will not live to the Blessings of Peace, and suffer, as the Examples of the Christian Faith did suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, for their Testimonies in the Peace of the Gospel, such incur in that State the Judgments of God both upon themselves and Neighbours; and as afore-written, Christ's Sermon in the Mount, he there sheweth who are blessed, and <hi>he opened his Mouth and taught the Disciples and the Multitude present, saying, Blessed are the poor in Spirit, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven; and blessed are they that mourn, for they shall be comforted; blessed are the Meek, for they shall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Earth; blessed are they which do hunger and thirst after Righteousness, for they shall be filled; blessed are the Merciful, for they shall obtain Mercy; blessed are the pure in Heart, for they shall see God; blessed are the Peace-makers, for they shall be called the Children of God; blessed are they which are persecuted for Righteousness-sake, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven; and blessed are ye when Men revile you and persecute you falsly for my Name-sake,</hi> Mat. ch. 5. and after all these Blessings he saith, <hi>One jot or one tittle of the Law shall not pass away till all be fulfilled:</hi> And that the Commandments is the great Law which Jesus treated upon, is plain, the Pharisee asked, <hi>What good Thing shall I do that I may have eternal Life?</hi> And the Answer was, <hi>If thou wilt enter into Life, keep the Commandments; and he said, Which? And Jesus answered and said, Thou shalt do no Murder; thou shalt not commit Adultery; thou shalt not Steal; thou shalt not bear false Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness against thy Neighbour; honour thy Father and thy Mother; and thou shalt love thy Neighbour as thy self,</hi> Mat. 19.18, 19. and one of the Scribes asked him, <hi>Which is the first Commandment of all? And he answered, The first of all the Commandments is, Hear O Israel, the Lord our God is one Lord,</hi> Mark 12.29. (Deut. 6.4.) <hi>and thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Mind, and with all thy Strength; this is the first Commandment, and the second is like, namely this, Thou shalt love thy Neighbour as thy self; there is none other greater Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments than these:</hi> and a Lawyer asking. <hi>Which is the great Commandment in the Law?</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the same Answer, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.26. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.25. <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.13. and the great Example of the Christian Faith is, to bless them that curse you, and love your Enemies, do good to them that hate you, and to them that despitefully use you and persecute you: and to be perfect in the universal Spirit, which will gather all Nations; and in that Spirit of Love in the Truth, to be perfect in Love to all, as your Father which is in Heaven is perfect and good to all; and Christ came to save Mens Lives, and not to destroy them; and the Law points to Obedience, and keeping the Commandments of God, and the Covenants which are given in his Grace, to support his People, that they may renew their Strength, and live for ever in the support of his Grace; and to keep his Statutes, which Statutes of Love and Mercy, and the Commandments are united together; and to love the Lord thy God, (and saith the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, <hi>Thou shalt love thy Neighbour as thy self</hi>) and in the Love of God, not to covet any thing that is thy Neighbours, nor to bear false Witness against thy Neighbour, and to honour thy Father and Mother that thy Days may be long in the Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee; and these Commandments and Statutes are in the Path-way to Life, under both the Law and Gospel; and to obey the Commandments and Statutes, and the Covenant in the Commandments, is entering Christ's Kingdom of Peace, which leads to the Father in the Peace of Obedience, to live for ever in the Works of the Spirit, as the Works of the Spirit
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:189133:18"/> is obeyed, so to rest in Spirit by Obedience, and to follow the Example the Lord Creator hath given to keep his Holy Rest, and hath put it into a Command, that his great Command should be obeyed; but to live neither to the Commandments of God, and the Peace there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained (to them which keep Covenant with God) and obey his Statutes in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, neither obey the Gospel of Peace, then the Judgments upon the Generations will be just, and the Wrath of God and the Lamb will break forth hot upon one Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion after another; and they that live not to the Gospel, bring themselves under the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of both the Law and the Gospel; and, saith <hi>Moses, Know therefore that the Lord thy God he is God, the faithful God, which keepeth Covenant and Mercy with them that love him and keep his Commandments to a thousand Generations, and repayeth them that hate him to their Face, to destroy them he will not be slack,</hi> Deut. 7.9. so as the Measure of every Generation is full, for their Disobedience to both the Law and Gospel the Lord, will visit the World in Judgments, till they come to see his Kingdom of Mercy and Peace, by being obedient to his Will, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on these Terms he hath sent his Son to bless his People that obey him and keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; and <hi>Moses</hi>'s Exhortation to the People is, <hi>Thou shalt teach them diligently unto thy Children, and shalt talk of them when thou sittest in thine House, and when thou walkest by the Way, and when thou lieth down, and when thou risest up, and thou shalt bind them for a Sign upon thine Hands, and they shall be as Frontlets between thine Eyee, and thou shalt write them upon the Posts of thy House,</hi> Deut. 6.7, 8, 9. and this was not only to the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> going in to possess the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but to every Generation after to teach their Children, for the Lord's Mercy to them that keep his Commandments is promised to a thousand Generations of them that love him, and his hate also to them that hate him and keep not his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. It needs no Inspiration to wait to know whether any People should keep the Ten Commandments, because they are to be teached to their Children from Generation to Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; and the Lord's promises of Mercy is to a thousand Generations of them that love him, and to repay his hate to such Generations that after they are teached keep not the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God; and remember the Angel in the <hi>Revelations</hi> to <hi>John</hi> hath foretold, <hi>The Dragon was Wrath and persecuted the Woman,</hi> (that is the Church) <hi>and went to make War with the remnant of her Seed, which keep the Commandments of God, and have the Testimony of Jesus Christ;</hi> so the Commandments, and to have the Faith of Jesus Christ is not to be separated, and a good Foundation is laid for keeping the Lord's Rest; first, as afore-written, after his great and glorious six Days work, he kept it himself; and when he called the Church, he shewed a Miracle in raining of Manna from Heaven, to confirm the Church in the keeping his Rest; <hi>and after appeared upon Mount Sinai, with Thundrings, and Lightnings, and a thick Cloud upon the Mountain; and Mount Sinai was altogether on a Smoke, because the Lord descended upon it in Fire, and the Mountain quaked greatly; and when the Voice of the Trumpet sounded long, and waxed louder and louder, Moses spake, and God answered him by a Voice; and all the People saw the Thunderings, and Lightnings, and the Noise of the Trumpet, and the Mountain smoking:</hi> So the Lord confirmed the Church by shewing of Miracles, and they heard the Voice of his Words and promised Obedience; and every Generation is to learn and teach their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and obey the Voice; and for Sin and Disobedience the World will provoke the Lord to let in his Fiery Appearance of which they were once afraid, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. <hi>and</hi> 5.25. as <hi>Israel,</hi> when they heard the Lord's Voice out of the midst of the Fire, saying, <hi>This great Fire will consume us, if we hear the Voice of the Lord our God any more, then we shall die;</hi> so they heard the Covenant, and notwithstanding the new Covenant is writ in the Heart, and put in the Mind, yet that does not abolish the keeping the Ten Commandments of the Lord thy God. And the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> which foretels, <hi>The Law shall be written in the Heart, and put in the inward Parts;</hi> he calls also <hi>to keep the Sabbath,</hi> ch. 17.20, 27. and the Prophet speaking of the new Covenant, and the Apostle making the first Covenant old; the first Covenant, that is, of Offerings to be accepted as Atonements for Sin, he then shews the new Covenant writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:189133:18"/> in the Heart, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 31.31, 32, 33, 34. and that by Christ's eternal Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood the Levitical Priesthood is abolished, and the Temporal Covenant by the Eternal; and the Apostle sheweth, That when <hi>Solomon</hi> had built a House to praise the Lord in, there were Ordinances of Divine Service and a Worldly Sanctuary, for there was a Tabernacle made first, wherein was the Candlestick, and the Table, and the Shew-Bread, which is called the Sanctuary, and the second Vail had the Golden Censor, (a Testimony against them which offered false Fire, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.46. and <hi>ch.</hi> 17.10.) and the Golden Pot that had Manna; (a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the Miracle wrought when the Lord called the Church to keep his Rest) and <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod that budded and blossomed, to shew God's Power and Servants from them that rebelled against him; and these Things were kept in the Tabernacle of Witnesses near the Oracle, as Remembrances of God's Power and Faithfulness to uphold his Church; and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> received the Tables of Testimony, the Tables of Stone, and put them in the Ark, and <hi>there was nothing in the Ark save the two Tables of Stone, which Moses put there at Horib, when the Lord made a Covenant with the Children of Israel when they came out of the Land of Egypt,</hi> 1 Kings 8.9, 21. and <hi>Moses</hi> bears Witness, <hi>The Tables were the Work of God, and the Writing was the Writing of God graven upon the Tables,</hi> Exod. 32.16. And after the Lord indued <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> with Wisdom to build him a House to praise his Name in, the Tabernacle was ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the Works of God's Power, and the Testimonies were laid up in the Ark, and the Glory of the Lord filled the Temple; and this visible Building points to the new and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Building which comes down from Heaven, from God, <hi>having the Glory of God;</hi> and in this City the Lord God and the Lamb are the Temple of it; <hi>and this City had no need of the Sun, neither of the Moon to shine in it, for the Glory of God did lighten it, and the Lamb is the Light thereof,</hi> Revel. 21.11, 23. and this spiritual Building will exceed the Glory of the former which <hi>Solomon</hi> built; and it is the same God which sanctifies his People, and builds up his spiritual House: And saith the Apostle, as speaking of Burnt-Offerings and Sacrifices, <hi>If the first Covenant had been faultless, then should no place have been found for the second; but these Offerings has no relation to the Lord's holy Rest, that is for ever pure, and without fault, and to be kept holy.</hi> The Power of God which appeared in <hi>Moses</hi> was a Light to the World, and his Obedience to the Power shines to this Day; and <hi>Moses</hi> obeyed the Angel of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which covenanted with him and the People in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and coming out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and did give Signs and do Wonders before <hi>Pharoah,</hi> and in the sight of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> to confirm the Worship of the true God by his Power which they saw was with them; and <hi>Israel</hi> was led by the Right-Hand of <hi>Moses,</hi> with the glorious Arm of God's Power, through the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of Power, for the Lord refusing to go in Person, he sent the Angel of his Presence, the Angel of his Power in his Name, and promised to give them rest, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.14. and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Lord appeared in the Bush, and represents the Person of God, for the Word through the Angel said, <hi>I am the God of thy Father, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob;</hi> and the Angel of his Presence did Covenant with the People in the Lord's Name, and the Name of the Lord was proclaimed before them, and his Goodness to pass before them, and the Lord owned the Covenant, saying, <hi>I am the Lord thy God which brought thee out of the Land of Egypt, out of the House of Bondage,</hi> (that is, you came out by my Power) <hi>with Signs, and Miracles, and terrible Judgments:</hi> And as the Angel of God's Presence was with <hi>Moses,</hi> confirming the People by Signs and Miracles, to know the one true God and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship him; so the Angel of God's Presence was with Jesus, the great Prophet, like unto <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> and the Work of the Power appeared in him by Signs and Miracles wrought in the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, to confirm the Work in the Gospel Dispensation, and <hi>to worship the one God in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and in Truth,</hi> John 4.24. and the Power and Peace of the Words which he received of God, and gave to his Disciples, shines to this Day in the Gospel, which is Universal Love; and he is a holy Example under the Gospel, as was <hi>Moses</hi> under the Law; and to confirm the Gospel, he healed their Sicknesses, and dispossessed evil Spirits by the Word of God when pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:189133:19"/> with him, <hi>Luke</hi> 5.17. so that both the Law and Gospel is confirmed, shewing the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the one God, and the Power of God Christ the Lord, the Angel of his Presence, the Angel of the Covenant is leading up the Flock to the Father, to as many as follow the holy Example of Jesus and his Obedience; and Jesus was a Light to the World whilst in the World; and 'tis the one God which gives every Light, and the one God is to be distinguish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from every Lord and Servant sent with the Words of God, for which Words sake they were called Lord, as speaking in the Light the Words of God; but the one God is the Lord Creator of Heaven and Earth, the Sea and the Fountains of Water, the great Deep, the Lord of Hosts is his Name, and his Word is the great <hi>Messias,</hi> telling all Things to this Day, the Deliverer of his People that trust in his Arm; and as the Law was the School-Master to lead up the Flock to Christ, so they which are teached in Christ's School, he leads them to God even the Father, dictating the Mind and Will of God to them by the Inspirations of his Word, the Law of the Spirit, which Law gives Light to know God even the Father, and Christ in Jesus, and Jesus in Christ; and the Law of the Spirit is a fresh visitation of the Word, to know God and his holy One▪ that is, the holy Spirit received from the one God, the Words of God sent in errant to do his Will; and in which Word Jesus was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed with the Holy Ghost, and he teached his Disciples in that Word; he was led in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by the Holy Ghost; he baptized with the holy Ghost; he was conceived or created in the Womb by the Power of the Holy Ghost, (yet the Person of the Holy Ghost is not Flesh) but a Representation of the Holy Power and Spirit, a Light sent down to teach and instruct and inspire Men, for all glorious Appearances descends from Heaven, and it is God which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals Secrets, and opens Mysteries; and none knows the Father but the Son, and to whom the Son will reveal the Father; and the Son which reveals the Father is Spirit, as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is Spirit; so knowing the Church is in God, and the Pillar and Ground is Truth in keeping the Commandments (under both the Law and Gospel); and in keeping the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and the Lord's holy Rest contained therein, is joyning to the Lord in Worship, and to that Church above, which will yet throw them down below which don't keep to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and Truth in the Gospel of Peace, according to the Commandments; and the Father is to be obeyed through the Son, and my Prayer to God is, to hold out to the end, and to honour the Father in the Spirit of the Son, which finds acceptance with the Father; and to keep the Commandments of God, and live in the Peace of the Gospel, as believing and well-knowing, there is Power in God to defend the Faith he gives; and my Message to the World is, for Acts of Charity, Peace and Love, and to call to Repentance, and to serve and obey the living God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Elizabeth Redford.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 6. Line 31. for <hi>so</hi> r. <hi>see.</hi> ibid. l. 35. r. <hi>and as Christ.</hi> p. 8. l. 14. for <hi>Army</hi> r. <hi>Arm.</hi> p 9. l. 39. r. <hi>John</hi> 17.3. ibid. l. 47. for <hi>sixth Day</hi> r. <hi>six Days.</hi> p. 11. l. 24. after <hi>Love</hi> r. <hi>and.</hi> ibid. l. 28. for <hi>Angelick Present</hi> r. <hi>Angelical Presence.</hi> p. 12. l. 34. r. <hi>remains in their Rest.</hi> p. 13. l. 2. after <hi>was</hi> r. <hi>created.</hi> ibid. l. 49. r. <hi>confirm them.</hi> p. 14. l. 43. for <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> r. <hi>Command.</hi> p. 18. l. 38. for <hi>they Jews</hi> r. <hi>the Jews.</hi> p. 20. l. 28. for <hi>Titles</hi> r. <hi>Tipes.</hi> ibid. l. 45. for <hi>than</hi> r. <hi>in.</hi> ibid. l. 46. for <hi>of</hi> r. <hi>is.</hi> ibid. l. 47. r. <hi>does not.</hi> p. 22. l. 40. dele <hi>as.</hi> p. 23. l. 9. for <hi>Life</hi> r. <hi>five.</hi> p. 24. l. 20. for <hi>inured</hi> r. <hi>indued.</hi> p. 27. l. 18. after <hi>well</hi> r. <hi>when there was no Sun.</hi> p. 31. l. 46. after <hi>Child</hi> r. <hi>shall.</hi> p. 32. l. 24. before <hi>Majesty</hi> r. <hi>Voice of the.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>